<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - presentations</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/presentations.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>What Does Probability have to do with God?</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2023/Oct/18/what-does-probability-have-to-do-with-god/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2023-10-18:/posts/2023/Oct/18/what-does-probability-have-to-do-with-god/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will present a framework for rational inquiry based on probability theory. Probability theory is a branch of mathematics that deals with uncertainty and how to reason …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will present a framework for rational inquiry based on probability theory. Probability theory is a branch of mathematics that deals with uncertainty and how to reason about it. I will explain the basic concepts and principles of probability, and how they can be applied to any domain of interest, including theology, the study of the nature of God and religious beliefs. I will explore some of the key theological concepts, such as belief, faith, miracles, and the existence of God, and how they can be analyzed using probability. I will also compare and contrast the scientific method with other ways of acquiring knowledge, such as revelation and intuition. My aim is to provide a clear and consistent way of thinking about these topics, and to reveal the hidden assumptions and implications of various theological arguments. Along the way, I will demonstrate some surprising and counterintuitive results that arise from probability theory, and how they can lead to errors in reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://calendar.mit.edu/event/probability_and_god"&gt;https://calendar.mit.edu/event/probability_and_god&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/static/MIT Talk - Oct 2023.pdf"&gt;pdf of the talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/RFq1134pIc4?si=Q9OnMzMN1BkcbDDy"&gt;video of the talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category></entry><entry><title>What is Science?</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jul/29/what-is-science/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-07-29:/posts/2014/Jul/29/what-is-science/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I gave &lt;a href="pdf/What%20is%20Science.pdf"&gt;a presentation on the general topic of "What is Science?"&lt;/a&gt;  After some brief remarks about what science isn't and some of the factors (such as attitude) which …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I gave &lt;a href="pdf/What%20is%20Science.pdf"&gt;a presentation on the general topic of "What is Science?"&lt;/a&gt;  After some brief remarks about what science isn't and some of the factors (such as attitude) which reflects the best of science, I had the audience of around 16 students perform tests on automatic flushing toilets.  The exercise, which I &lt;a href="http://scitation.aip.org/content/aapt/journal/tpt/49/3/10.1119/1.3555503"&gt;published before&lt;/a&gt;, is a great way of getting at all of the concepts of experimental verification without any specialize equipment or preparation - the perfect platform for an informal talk or class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then tried to show some things that we are confident work (and why) and things that we are confident &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; work (and why) and finally some things where the picture is a bit fuzzier.  I'd prefer to have at least one more example of something non-trivial that we are confident works, for which the data is accessible. I use vaccines as an example, given its rising popularity and relevance in the news, but I'd love to have another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category></entry><entry><title>Statistical Heresies - The Movie</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jun/11/statistical-heresies-the-movie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-06-11:/posts/2014/Jun/11/statistical-heresies-the-movie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The moment we've been all waiting for, Statistical Heresies the movie is out!  You can watch it in a couple of places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/lL1LdNxhDnU"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;: You can hear me, but you might …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The moment we've been all waiting for, Statistical Heresies the movie is out!  You can watch it in a couple of places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/lL1LdNxhDnU"&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;: You can hear me, but you might want to &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/1h8q8lj42w1bnxzqogohc/Statistical-Heresies.pdf?rlkey=l2mxnqu9mjayfvv3kof13awqi&amp;amp;dl=0"&gt;download the pdf here&lt;/a&gt; to follow along.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk highlights some of the current Bayesian/frequentist relationships as they relate to introductory statistics education.  The discussion includes faculty from math, finance, environmental science, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a world where analytics in the form of statistical 
inference is playing a signiﬁcant role, from predicting 
elections, learning patterns in shopping habits, ﬁnding the 
genetic sources for diseases, and recognizing voice for 
computer control. Despite these successes, there is a serious 
disconnect between the best practices in the industry and 
what is typically taught at the undergraduate level. This 
faculty development seminar will introduce this problem, 
explore its history, present its causes, and make some modest 
proposals to solving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category></entry><entry><title>Statistical Heresies</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/May/22/statistical-heresies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-05-22:/posts/2014/May/22/statistical-heresies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm giving a talk today, highlighting some of the current Bayesian/frequentist relationships as they relate to introductory statistics education.  You can &lt;a href="pdf/Statistical%20Heresies.pdf"&gt;download the pdf here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm giving a talk today, highlighting some of the current Bayesian/frequentist relationships as they relate to introductory statistics education.  You can &lt;a href="pdf/Statistical%20Heresies.pdf"&gt;download the pdf here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a world where analytics in the form of statistical 
inference is playing a signiﬁcant role, from predicting 
elections, learning patterns in shopping habits, ﬁnding the 
genetic sources for diseases, and recognizing voice for 
computer control. Despite these successes, there is a serious 
disconnect between the best practices in the industry and 
what is typically taught at the undergraduate level. This 
faculty development seminar will introduce this problem, 
explore its history, present its causes, and make some modest 
proposals to solving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One comment after the fact - every single claim I made about why Bayes is not taught was demonstrated in the seminar.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="presentations"></category></entry></feed>