<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - productivity</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/productivity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2023-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>How NaNoWriMo Got Me Back to the Gym</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2023/Nov/14/how-nanowrimo-got-me-back-to-the-gym/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2023-11-14:/posts/2023/Nov/14/how-nanowrimo-got-me-back-to-the-gym/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So National Novel Writing Month (&lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt;) is here, and it has its usual ups and downs as expected.  For this event, you commit to writing 50,000 words of a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So National Novel Writing Month (&lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt;) is here, and it has its usual ups and downs as expected.  For this event, you commit to writing 50,000 words of a new novel during the month of November.  I first did it in 2019 - "won" it, achieving the 50,000 words of an admittedly terrible novel.  2020 was, well, 2020 as we all know.  2021 I rewrote the original one, by hand,  which improved it quite a bit, and then over the course of a year transcribed it.  I found that handwriting it had some definite benefits.  I felt that I could turn off my internal editor more effectively, I was less likely to get distracted because I was away from the technology, I could squeeze in writing during times that would be awkward or impossible to use a computer (e.g. watching a concert on TV with the family, waiting in the car to pick someone up, etc...), and I think there is some non-tangible benefit to the physical process of handwriting that I can't put my finger on.  The next year, 2022, I decided I didn't have the time and then this year I roped a few others into doing it to help me stay motivated.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far this month I have been doing well, keeping to 1700 words a day (9 handwritten pages of 190 words).  Saturday I had a demotivation point where I was frustrated with the way the story was going, wondering if I was wasting my time doing this at all when I have other work I should be doing.  Perhaps this was just a procrastination technique of mine to work on something other than the things that were pressing.  Also, I felt that while I enjoy a good story, I find it very difficult to come up with good ones myself.  I can't visualize things as clearly as I've heard others can, I find that my resolutions tent to be simplistic yet I don't know the best way to handle this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, I do like imagining other worlds, other characters.  I like the exploration of these new places and people, but I know I can't do everything I'd like to do in life -- I have to choose, so what to choose?  The good thing about &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; is the commitment to write, to look to produce volume rather than focus on quality.  It is this permission to write something bad that is motivating -- and gives the raw material to improve afterward.  It is the experimenting, and playing with words, that might get one to be better.  It is the act of showing up each day to do something challenging, but not overwhelming, where the cumulative effect across a month is something substantial that has value.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when I was demotivated, I wrote about writing itself, about the frustrations.  I wrote about how parts of the story weren't working and what might fix them or at least make them a little less bad.  It was my internal editor, but I felt I needed to voice it because the problems in the story were building and making it worse.  I then outlined the entire plot, so perhaps I could work on parts of it out of order.  I gave myself permission to write about other things, to be what is called a &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; Rebel -- someone who writes 50,000 words in a month, but not all on the novel, or even at all on the novel, but progresses their writing farther.  I gave myself the permission to write short stories -- perhaps poking at different ideas would help give me the confidence again.  Perhaps exploring a small, focused story would help me work on specific things like description or dialog without getting bogged down in world building or long plot lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt;, I started getting the virtual badges from the site -- first post, first 5k words, 3 day streak, etc...  I had won all these badges before, except one -- to post 1667 words every day, so i had my sights set on that.  I wasn't focused on the total, I was focused on the &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt;.  When I look at building a habit like this, I recall books on productivity that have been of help to me in the past.  &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear and &lt;a href="https://bulletjournal.com/pages/book"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bullet Journal Method&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Ryder Carroll are two such books, so I reread both of those over the past couple of weeks.   I'm a slow reader, but I accomplished this by listening to audiobooks while working in the yard, or driving here and there.  These books get me thinking about &lt;em&gt;systems&lt;/em&gt; as opposed to &lt;em&gt;goals&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; forces one to face both.  The goal of 50,000 words is there, but because it is so daunting, requiring a sustained regular effort across the month one has to examine ones systems for accomplishing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my previous &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; accomplishments, I feel that it hasn't been an entire success for me.  Sure, I finished a draft of a novel that I am reasonably proud of (which took 3 years) but my writing habit didn't sustain past November each time.  I could buckle down, get something that has value pretty much only to me (a novel that is pretty basic at best) but there isn't lasting value I think to others, and perhaps not even to me.  Or at least not as much value as I'd like to see.  In a way, I think it probably worth more to post 1700 words daily on this blog for a month, exploring various random topics.  That would be something of value I think.  Perhaps I should write a new paper to submit to a journal (or maybe get a couple papers out the door that have been languishing due to me not having a good system in place).   I like fiction, but find it hard to get into a new fiction series or book.  I read much more nonfiction, listen to many more podcasts and seminars, and re-read or listen to fiction I'm comfortable with (e.g. Lord of the Rings, Dune, Babylon 5, Chronicles of Thomas Covenant, etc...) rather than starting something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I do appreciate the fact that there is a common motivation this month to accomplish something big.  When I was looking at my habits, I noticed that I had stopped exercising and have been gaining weight or at least gaining a more spherical shape for the same weight.  In my exploration of habits, I was motivated by YouTuber &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@JamesDunne"&gt;James Dunne&lt;/a&gt; to look into how to work some &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/bLdrCTponaE?si=IxNf7-hM94ASMbvM"&gt;strength into my routines&lt;/a&gt;, but keeping it simple.  I was looking at various exercise routings, and came across the &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/nnf1YyMB39g?si=3nRVrMhIkEff7XjD"&gt;The Only Five Exercises You Need&lt;/a&gt; video, and there was a phrase in the comments to the video: "Stay fit, age is not the barrier. Attitude is. Overcome it"  At about the same time,  I was talking to my friend who exercises a lot (much more than I have time for) and I asked him about his routine.  He said that he gets up early, around 4:45am, and goes for a run -- minimum 5 miles -- and then in the afternoon he goes to the gym for weights.  The magnitude was more than I would want, or be able, to do given my other commitments but it was the other things that he said that really struck me.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He runs regardless of the weather.  That way there is no question about whether he will run on a given day.  He said the hardest thing is getting out of bed in the morning, and pulling on the running clothes.  But he just does it.  I asked what happens if he starts thinking "Oh, I just want to sleep in today." and he replied that he doesn't allow that.  He also said that he runs not for the physical benefits but for the mental benefits -- to clear his head.  Finally, he said, that once he has done the hardest thing in the day -- waking up, and running in 23 degree weather, that the rest of the day doesn't seem that hard.  That was the final pin that got pulled for me.  I was looking at habits due to &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt;, looking to accomplish something great, and it had brought me to the realization of how to revamp my exercise.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past three days -- and I hope for the foreseeable future -- I have gotten up early, around 5am, 20 minutes of strength (from the &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/nnf1YyMB39g?si=3nRVrMhIkEff7XjD"&gt;The Only Five Exercises You Need&lt;/a&gt; video, mostly, but also some from James Dunne's video &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/bLdrCTponaE?si=ts3nsQxOgwMsrr06"&gt;12 Minute Strength Workout for Runners (INJURY PREVENTION)&lt;/a&gt;), then 20 minutes of running outside.  No treadmill allowed, no excuses.  I'm sore, but not injured -- which I hope the strength exercises will help me keep the injuries away.  &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; teaches us that a concerted effort every day can accomplish large effects over time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that I need to be honest with myself, and there is more value in some things than others.  I wrote 0 words yesterday, so I won't be getting the "1667 words every day badge".  But I am fine with that.  I had a day where I ran 2 miles in 23 degree weather before anyone was awake, taught 4 classes, had 3 meetings, and gave a research talk.  At the end of the day, I had a choice of either working on NaNo to get that badge or to go out with my friends to relax.  I chose my friends.    There are some things more important, and one can't do everything that one wants to do.  There are too many interesting things in this life, and one has to choose between them.  That is not a bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; forces one to face priorities and systems, while it teaches us valuable lessons about the power of consistent work toward a goal.  I've decided to be a &lt;a href="http://nanowrimo.org"&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt; Rebel this year, doing the 50,000 words for the month, but not necessarily on the novel itself.  In fact, probably not mostly on the novel.  This post is my 1700 words for today.  Have a great day!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="writing"></category></entry><entry><title>There is more than enough time</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/May/24/there-is-more-than-enough-time/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-05-24:/posts/2018/May/24/there-is-more-than-enough-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/benjamin-p-hardy/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re with your friends, be with your friends. If you’re doing the dishes …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/benjamin-p-hardy/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re with your friends, be with your friends. If you’re doing the dishes, do the dishes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Things Are A Dime-A-Dozen&lt;/strong&gt;.  For me, passively watching a movie with my kids is good. However, actively engaging with them—whether playing games, laughing, playing out in the yard—is better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with doing good things is that they are easy to justify, because they are inherently good. But, as Jim Collins, author of Good To Great, has said, “Good is the enemy of great. Few people attain great lives, in large part because it is just so easy to settle for a good life.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always Take The Higher Road&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the alarm clock goes off , do you push snooze or get up? When you’re with your spouse, do you compliment or criticize? Do you listen, or must you always speak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Who You Ideally Want To Become, Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Bill Walsh has said, “Winners act like winners before they become winners.” That’s how they become “winners.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take time to write down your core values and goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Exploring the Idea of Scrum</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/May/18/exploring-the-idea-of-scrum/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-05-18:/posts/2018/May/18/exploring-the-idea-of-scrum/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although I am not in software development, and I don't work in a lot of teams, I have recently read the book &lt;em&gt;Scrum: The Art of Doing Twice the Work …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although I am not in software development, and I don't work in a lot of teams, I have recently read the book &lt;em&gt;Scrum: The Art of Doing Twice the Work in Half the Time&lt;/em&gt; (https://www.scruminc.com/new-scrum-the-book/) which I find very interesting and possibly quite useful&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  As far as I can tell, the Scrum process derives its value from a few key concepts, which can equally well apply to individuals as well as teams, to academia as well as software development.  These key concepts, as I see them is, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work is done in a short, cyclical pattern: 1-2 week "sprints"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The work - the goals, on deck (aka backlog), work in progress, and done - is &lt;em&gt;displayed publicly&lt;/em&gt; (or at least prominently to the team) &lt;em&gt;at all times&lt;/em&gt;.  This is typically done with a physical &lt;a href="https://manifesto.co.uk/agile-concepts-scrum-task-board/"&gt;scrum board&lt;/a&gt;, but can also be done in software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;demonstration&lt;/em&gt; occurs at the end a work "sprint".  The result of the sprint is something &lt;em&gt;deliverable&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt;, even if small, and this is demonstrate to the people to whom the work has value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;review of the process and results&lt;/em&gt; occurs regularly at the end of each sprint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If working on a team, we add the further concept&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A team needs to have &lt;em&gt;absolutely everyone&lt;/em&gt; who is needed to complete the work.  This will often involve people at many levels of a hierarchy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an addition, there are a few other things I learned from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role of management is to &lt;em&gt;remove the impediments&lt;/em&gt; to getting projects done.  So, part of the review process is to list the impediments to the work so that management can work on that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short (15-minute) "scrum" meetings answering "what have I done since the last, what are my impediments, what am I going to get done"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focussing on &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; rather than work is more productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "deliver quickly" and adapt is a better strategy than trying to deliver a large, complete, and possibly incorrect product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile I am also working my way through the book &lt;em&gt;Agile Faculty: Practical Strategies for Managing Research, Service and Teaching.&lt;/em&gt; (http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/A/bo26106581.html) I'm interested if any of these ideas will help in my own practices, and whether I can gain some benefit for the department and university processes with these ideas.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One summary is &lt;a href="http://mightyrasing.com/notes-on-scrum-the-art-of-doing-twice-the-work-in-half-the-time/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>More than Enough Time</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Feb/02/more-than-enough-time/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-02:/posts/2018/Feb/02/more-than-enough-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://journal.thriveglobal.com/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time-you-have-3ffa7adaa5d3"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're with your friends, be with your friends. If you're doing the dishes, do the …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://journal.thriveglobal.com/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time-you-have-3ffa7adaa5d3"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're with your friends, be with your friends. If you're doing the dishes, do the dishes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Things Are A Dime-A-Dozen&lt;/strong&gt;.  For me, passively watching a movie with my kids is good. However, actively engaging with them---whether playing games, laughing, playing out in the yard---is better.
*The problem with doing good things is that they are easy to justify, because they are inherently good. But, as Jim Collins, author of Good To Great, has said, "Good is the enemy of great. Few people attain great lives, in large part because it is just so easy to settle for a good life."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always Take The Higher Road&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the alarm clock goes off , do you push snooze or get up? When you're with your spouse, do you compliment or criticize? Do you listen, or must you always speak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Who You Ideally Want To Become, Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Bill Walsh has said, "Winners act like winners before they become winners." That's how they become "winners."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take time to write down your core values and goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons from Jon Acuff's book Finish</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/17/lessons-from-jon-acuffs-book-finish/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-17:/posts/2018/Jan/17/lessons-from-jon-acuffs-book-finish/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the lessons I learned from &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Jon Acuff's book &lt;em&gt;Finish&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut Your Goal in Half&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half done is better than none, psychologically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose what to bomb&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what gives?  something …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the lessons I learned from &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Jon Acuff's book &lt;em&gt;Finish&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut Your Goal in Half&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half done is better than none, psychologically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose what to bomb&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what gives?  something will, and that's ok.  it's called "seasons".  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;just say "no"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simplify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it fun if you want it done&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give yourself rewards.  This is also in "The Power of Habit"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get rid of secret rules&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid rules like "I'm not a ...."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use data to celebrate imperfect progress&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track time, pages, words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track miles run, pounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;books sold, thank you notes mailed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new contacts, books read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the day before done&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other ideas creep in - write them down for later, and don't let them derail you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these ideas are your next project!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;afraid of finishing?  don't be!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be related to the Art of Charm toolbox podcast episode &lt;a href="https://theartofcharm.com/podcast-episodes/aoc-toolbox-quality-want-focus-quantity-episode-683/"&gt;If Quality Is What You Want, Focus on Quantity (Episode 683)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>How to be productive - Part 2 - Methods</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/16/how-to-be-productive-part-2-methods/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-16:/posts/2018/Jan/16/how-to-be-productive-part-2-methods/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=""&gt;Part 1 of this series&lt;/a&gt; I describe some of the apps I've used.  Here I speak about some of the methods I have tried to be productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-list"&gt;The List …&lt;/h3&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=""&gt;Part 1 of this series&lt;/a&gt; I describe some of the apps I've used.  Here I speak about some of the methods I have tried to be productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-list"&gt;The List&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a list of some of the resources
* &lt;a href="https://gettingthingsdone.com/"&gt;GTD (Getting things done)&lt;/a&gt; - this is perhaps the universal "To Do" methodology.  Most people seem to have a love/hate relationship with this method.
* &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/zen-to-done-ztd-the-ultimate-simple-productivity-system/"&gt;Zen to Done&lt;/a&gt; - a simplification of the GTD method.
* &lt;a href="https://12weekyear.com/"&gt;12 Week Year&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Finish by Jon Acuff&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="https://theartofcharm.com/"&gt;The Art of Charm Podcast&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="http://www.asianefficiency.com/podcast/"&gt;The Productivity Show&lt;/a&gt; - excellent, specific advice on productivity
* &lt;a href="http://productivity-podcast.com/"&gt;Kevin Kruse - Extreme Productivity&lt;/a&gt; - podcast seems to be over, but binge listen to this!
* &lt;a href="https://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/pomodoro-technique.htm"&gt;Pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-takeaway"&gt;The Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The filing system for resource materials described in GTD is golden. Basically, just alphabetically, one folder per letter.  Doesn't matter whether you are filing "pet alligators" with "asthma paper" because you know close to where you need to look (e.g. is "asthma" under "asthma" or "medical"?).  There usually isnt so much to look through that it takes long to find, and you &lt;strong&gt;simplify the filing so that you're more likely to do it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "2-minute rule" from GTD and zTD.  If it would take more less than 2 minutes to do, do it right now.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To-do's should be &lt;em&gt;actions&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;nouns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose your MIT (Most Important Todos) each day - 3 of them - and get them done first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is important to do, &lt;strong&gt;put it on your calendar&lt;/strong&gt;, in 15 minute blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pomodoro rocks!  25 minutes, for me, seems to be a good time-period for getting a single non-trivial thing done.  Trivial things (like email) can be done in 15 minute blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put "check email" on calendar, only for 2 specific times a day and don't look at it otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I am trying bullet journaling, I will post an update on that method, and how it compares to the digital methods I've tried.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>How to be productive - Part 1 - Apps</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/15/how-to-be-productive-part-1-apps/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-15:/posts/2018/Jan/15/how-to-be-productive-part-1-apps/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a to-do list app junkie, unfortunately.  Actually, beyond that, I am a &lt;em&gt;productivity method&lt;/em&gt; junkie. Of course, I recognize that in doing so I often make myself &lt;em&gt;less …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a to-do list app junkie, unfortunately.  Actually, beyond that, I am a &lt;em&gt;productivity method&lt;/em&gt; junkie. Of course, I recognize that in doing so I often make myself &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; productive.  Still it's a hard interest to shake.  Further, I find that when I switch to-do apps it makes it easier to throw out all kinds of items which I wasn't going to do anyway.  So I feel like I get a burst of productivity simply by switching to-do apps every 6 months to a year.  Here is a short list of the to-do apps I have tried, and some quick comments on them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; (current app) - good free app, but the premium is worth it.  I haven't used it for sharing to-do's but it has a clean interface and I can have it on my phone, mac, and windows tablet.  You need to pay for some features that Wunderlist has in the free - like reminders, comments, and attachments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wunderlist.com/"&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/a&gt; (former app) - nice free app, but seems to be aging a bit and there is no future support for it.  Microsoft hopes to replace it with their own To Do app. Doesn't archive projects at all (you have to delete them!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt; - a solid app, but mac/iphone only - and expensive!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ticktick.com/"&gt;Tick-tick&lt;/a&gt; (as of June 2017) - maximum of 9 lists or go pro with $25/mo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://asana.com/"&gt;Asana&lt;/a&gt; - looks interesting, but perhaps overkill as a to-do app - more for teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also tried, and rejected for various reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firetask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todo Pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Astrid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taskpaper - nice idea for text-based to-dos, but a bit fragile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OmniFocus - complete, huge learning curve, and quite pricey.  overkill for most of the things I need a to-do app to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I am going to try out an analog solution &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com/"&gt;with bullet journal&lt;/a&gt;, once I figure out how it works.  I'll report on what I find!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry></feed>