<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - productivity</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/productivity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2018-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>There is more than enough time</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/May/24/there-is-more-than-enough-time/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-05-24:/posts/2018/May/24/there-is-more-than-enough-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/benjamin-p-hardy/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re with your friends, be with your friends. If you’re doing the dishes …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/benjamin-p-hardy/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re with your friends, be with your friends. If you’re doing the dishes, do the dishes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Things Are A Dime-A-Dozen&lt;/strong&gt;.  For me, passively watching a movie with my kids is good. However, actively engaging with them—whether playing games, laughing, playing out in the yard—is better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with doing good things is that they are easy to justify, because they are inherently good. But, as Jim Collins, author of Good To Great, has said, “Good is the enemy of great. Few people attain great lives, in large part because it is just so easy to settle for a good life.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always Take The Higher Road&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the alarm clock goes off , do you push snooze or get up? When you’re with your spouse, do you compliment or criticize? Do you listen, or must you always speak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Who You Ideally Want To Become, Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Bill Walsh has said, “Winners act like winners before they become winners.” That’s how they become “winners.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take time to write down your core values and goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Exploring the Idea of Scrum</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/May/18/exploring-the-idea-of-scrum/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-05-18:/posts/2018/May/18/exploring-the-idea-of-scrum/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although I am not in software development, and I don't work in a lot of teams, I have recently read the book &lt;em&gt;Scrum: The Art of Doing Twice the Work …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although I am not in software development, and I don't work in a lot of teams, I have recently read the book &lt;em&gt;Scrum: The Art of Doing Twice the Work in Half the Time&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href="https://www.scruminc.com/new-scrum-the-book/"&gt;https://www.scruminc.com/new-scrum-the-book/&lt;/a&gt;) which I find very interesting and possibly quite useful&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  As far as I can tell, the Scrum process derives its value from a few key concepts, which can equally well apply to individuals as well as teams, to academia as well as software development.  These key concepts, as I see them is, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work is done in a short, cyclical pattern: 1-2 week "sprints"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The work - the goals, on deck (aka backlog), work in progress, and done - is &lt;em&gt;displayed publicly&lt;/em&gt; (or at least prominently to the team) &lt;em&gt;at all times&lt;/em&gt;.  This is typically done with a physical &lt;a href="https://manifesto.co.uk/agile-concepts-scrum-task-board/"&gt;scrum board&lt;/a&gt;, but can also be done in software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;demonstration&lt;/em&gt; occurs at the end a work "sprint".  The result of the sprint is something &lt;em&gt;deliverable&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;complete&lt;/em&gt;, even if small, and this is demonstrate to the people to whom the work has value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;review of the process and results&lt;/em&gt; occurs regularly at the end of each sprint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If working on a team, we add the further concept&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A team needs to have &lt;em&gt;absolutely everyone&lt;/em&gt; who is needed to complete the work.  This will often involve people at many levels of a hierarchy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an addition, there are a few other things I learned from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role of management is to &lt;em&gt;remove the impediments&lt;/em&gt; to getting projects done.  So, part of the review process is to list the impediments to the work so that management can work on that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short (15-minute) "scrum" meetings answering "what have I done since the last, what are my impediments, what am I going to get done"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focussing on &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; rather than work is more productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "deliver quickly" and adapt is a better strategy than trying to deliver a large, complete, and possibly incorrect product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile I am also working my way through the book &lt;em&gt;Agile Faculty: Practical Strategies for Managing Research, Service and Teaching.&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href="http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/A/bo26106581.html"&gt;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/A/bo26106581.html&lt;/a&gt;) I'm interested if any of these ideas will help in my own practices, and whether I can gain some benefit for the department and university processes with these ideas.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One summary is &lt;a href="http://mightyrasing.com/notes-on-scrum-the-art-of-doing-twice-the-work-in-half-the-time/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>More than Enough Time</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Feb/02/more-than-enough-time/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-02:/posts/2018/Feb/02/more-than-enough-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://journal.thriveglobal.com/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time-you-have-3ffa7adaa5d3"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're with your friends, be with your friends. If you're doing the dishes, do the …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes about time management that I found useful from &lt;a href="https://journal.thriveglobal.com/theres-more-than-enough-time-when-you-use-the-time-you-have-3ffa7adaa5d3"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're with your friends, be with your friends. If you're doing the dishes, do the dishes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Things Are A Dime-A-Dozen&lt;/strong&gt;.  For me, passively watching a movie with my kids is good. However, actively engaging with them---whether playing games, laughing, playing out in the yard---is better.
*The problem with doing good things is that they are easy to justify, because they are inherently good. But, as Jim Collins, author of Good To Great, has said, "Good is the enemy of great. Few people attain great lives, in large part because it is just so easy to settle for a good life."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always Take The Higher Road&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the alarm clock goes off , do you push snooze or get up? When you're with your spouse, do you compliment or criticize? Do you listen, or must you always speak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Who You Ideally Want To Become, Today&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Bill Walsh has said, "Winners act like winners before they become winners." That's how they become "winners."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take time to write down your core values and goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Lessons from Jon Acuff's book Finish</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/17/lessons-from-jon-acuffs-book-finish/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-17:/posts/2018/Jan/17/lessons-from-jon-acuffs-book-finish/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the lessons I learned from &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Jon Acuff's book &lt;em&gt;Finish&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut Your Goal in Half&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half done is better than none, psychologically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose what to bomb&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what gives?  something …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the lessons I learned from &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Jon Acuff's book &lt;em&gt;Finish&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut Your Goal in Half&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half done is better than none, psychologically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose what to bomb&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what gives?  something will, and that's ok.  it's called "seasons".  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;just say "no"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simplify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it fun if you want it done&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give yourself rewards.  This is also in "The Power of Habit"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get rid of secret rules&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid rules like "I'm not a ...."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use data to celebrate imperfect progress&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track time, pages, words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track miles run, pounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;books sold, thank you notes mailed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new contacts, books read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the day before done&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other ideas creep in - write them down for later, and don't let them derail you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these ideas are your next project!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;afraid of finishing?  don't be!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be related to the Art of Charm toolbox podcast episode &lt;a href="https://theartofcharm.com/podcast-episodes/aoc-toolbox-quality-want-focus-quantity-episode-683/"&gt;If Quality Is What You Want, Focus on Quantity (Episode 683)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>How to be productive - Part 2 - Methods</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/16/how-to-be-productive-part-2-methods/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-16:/posts/2018/Jan/16/how-to-be-productive-part-2-methods/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=""&gt;Part 1 of this series&lt;/a&gt; I describe some of the apps I've used.  Here I speak about some of the methods I have tried to be productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-list"&gt;The List …&lt;/h3&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=""&gt;Part 1 of this series&lt;/a&gt; I describe some of the apps I've used.  Here I speak about some of the methods I have tried to be productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-list"&gt;The List&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a list of some of the resources
* &lt;a href="https://gettingthingsdone.com/"&gt;GTD (Getting things done)&lt;/a&gt; - this is perhaps the universal "To Do" methodology.  Most people seem to have a love/hate relationship with this method.
* &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/zen-to-done-ztd-the-ultimate-simple-productivity-system/"&gt;Zen to Done&lt;/a&gt; - a simplification of the GTD method.
* &lt;a href="https://12weekyear.com/"&gt;12 Week Year&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="https://acuff.me/books/"&gt;Finish by Jon Acuff&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="https://theartofcharm.com/"&gt;The Art of Charm Podcast&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href="http://www.asianefficiency.com/podcast/"&gt;The Productivity Show&lt;/a&gt; - excellent, specific advice on productivity
* &lt;a href="http://productivity-podcast.com/"&gt;Kevin Kruse - Extreme Productivity&lt;/a&gt; - podcast seems to be over, but binge listen to this!
* &lt;a href="https://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/pomodoro-technique.htm"&gt;Pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-takeaway"&gt;The Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The filing system for resource materials described in GTD is golden. Basically, just alphabetically, one folder per letter.  Doesn't matter whether you are filing "pet alligators" with "asthma paper" because you know close to where you need to look (e.g. is "asthma" under "asthma" or "medical"?).  There usually isnt so much to look through that it takes long to find, and you &lt;strong&gt;simplify the filing so that you're more likely to do it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "2-minute rule" from GTD and zTD.  If it would take more less than 2 minutes to do, do it right now.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To-do's should be &lt;em&gt;actions&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;nouns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose your MIT (Most Important Todos) each day - 3 of them - and get them done first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is important to do, &lt;strong&gt;put it on your calendar&lt;/strong&gt;, in 15 minute blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pomodoro rocks!  25 minutes, for me, seems to be a good time-period for getting a single non-trivial thing done.  Trivial things (like email) can be done in 15 minute blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put "check email" on calendar, only for 2 specific times a day and don't look at it otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I am trying bullet journaling, I will post an update on that method, and how it compares to the digital methods I've tried.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>How to be productive - Part 1 - Apps</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/15/how-to-be-productive-part-1-apps/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-15:/posts/2018/Jan/15/how-to-be-productive-part-1-apps/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a to-do list app junkie, unfortunately.  Actually, beyond that, I am a &lt;em&gt;productivity method&lt;/em&gt; junkie. Of course, I recognize that in doing so I often make myself &lt;em&gt;less …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a to-do list app junkie, unfortunately.  Actually, beyond that, I am a &lt;em&gt;productivity method&lt;/em&gt; junkie. Of course, I recognize that in doing so I often make myself &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; productive.  Still it's a hard interest to shake.  Further, I find that when I switch to-do apps it makes it easier to throw out all kinds of items which I wasn't going to do anyway.  So I feel like I get a burst of productivity simply by switching to-do apps every 6 months to a year.  Here is a short list of the to-do apps I have tried, and some quick comments on them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; (current app) - good free app, but the premium is worth it.  I haven't used it for sharing to-do's but it has a clean interface and I can have it on my phone, mac, and windows tablet.  You need to pay for some features that Wunderlist has in the free - like reminders, comments, and attachments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wunderlist.com/"&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/a&gt; (former app) - nice free app, but seems to be aging a bit and there is no future support for it.  Microsoft hopes to replace it with their own To Do app. Doesn't archive projects at all (you have to delete them!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt; - a solid app, but mac/iphone only - and expensive!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ticktick.com/"&gt;Tick-tick&lt;/a&gt; (as of June 2017) - maximum of 9 lists or go pro with $25/mo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://asana.com/"&gt;Asana&lt;/a&gt; - looks interesting, but perhaps overkill as a to-do app - more for teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also tried, and rejected for various reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firetask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todo Pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Astrid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taskpaper - nice idea for text-based to-dos, but a bit fragile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OmniFocus - complete, huge learning curve, and quite pricey.  overkill for most of the things I need a to-do app to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I am going to try out an analog solution &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com/"&gt;with bullet journal&lt;/a&gt;, once I figure out how it works.  I'll report on what I find!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>