<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - projects</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/projects.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2019-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>A Measure of Faith - Probability in Religious Thought</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Jul/15/a-measure-of-faith-probability-in-religious-thought/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-07-15:/posts/2019/Jul/15/a-measure-of-faith-probability-in-religious-thought/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the trivial to the monumental our decisions are governed by – or should be governed by – rational thought. This book explores the role of rational thought as described by the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the trivial to the monumental our decisions are governed by – or should be governed by – rational thought. This book explores the role of rational thought as described by the rules of probability applied to the ideas in traditional religious discourse. It provides a basic introduction to the rules of probability for those who want a refresher and then proceeds to apply those rules to standard arguments for the existence of God, the resurrection of Jesus, the evidence for miracles, and the concept of faith. Through this exploration, a common thread of analysis is woven to describe notions of simplicity in explanations, independence of evidence, and the common cognitive biases we all share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-book"&gt;The Book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Amazon you can get &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Measure-Faith-Probability-Religious-Thought/dp/1099939143"&gt;the print book&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Measure-Faith-Probability-Religious-Thought-ebook/dp/B07SMB7RB4"&gt;the Kindle book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow me &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bblais"&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and ask me any questions!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="updates-free-for-a-year"&gt;Updates free for a year&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I envision this book to be a living document that I update as I expand topics, clarify the topics I have covered, and improve the examples.  If I make &lt;strong&gt;any updates&lt;/strong&gt; to the book in any way within a year, you can get a free update of an e-copy by contacting me at &lt;a href="mailto:bblais@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:bblais@gmail.com"&gt;bblais@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and providing some demonstration that you purchased it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="from-the-blog"&gt;From the Blog&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jul/24/faith-trust-and-evidence/"&gt;Faith, Trust, and Evidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... Tim McGrew and Peter Boghossian on the definition of faith and whether or not faith is a valid way of knowing. In this discussion, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jul/28/is-faith-the-same-as-trust-or-baseless-belief/"&gt;Is Faith the Same as Trust or Baseless Belief?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... Tim McGrew and Peter Boghossian on the definition of faith, and whether it is a valid way of knowing. I have my initial response ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Mar/13/how-to-dodge-the-consequences-of-belief/"&gt;How to Dodge the Consequences of Belief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... couple days, and can see why I had my initial impression. Faith They start with a discussion about the term faith , and McGrath ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2013/Oct/24/knowledge-faith-and-belief/"&gt;Knowledge, Faith, and Belief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... abound. It seems very common that a word like "faith" is used by different people for different ends, and the definition shifts even within ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2010/Jan/31/faith-and-science/"&gt;Faith and Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... Ken Miller makes the point that science should inform faith and faith should inform science. He cites Paul Davies, a physicist who has an ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jun/03/do-healing-miracles-happen/"&gt;Do healing miracles happen?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... don't. Here's the bottom line. Bottom line is it requires faith ...and faith is risk. And faith is a hard thing to risk." I ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Feb/12/scientific-knowledge/"&gt;Scientific Knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... ", the commenter says: I believe we all choose to have faith in one book or another. This is simply, and demonstrably, not true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2013/Mar/04/unbelievable-project-gods-existence-free-will-and-faith-the-big-questions/"&gt;Unbelievable Project: God's existence, free will and faith - The Big Questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6/22/07 - God's existence, free will and faith - The Big Questions As part of the Unbelievable Project , I am taking notes and "arm-chair" ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2013/Mar/08/unbelievable-project-god-delusion-debate-deluded-by-dawkins/"&gt;Unbelievable Project: God Delusion debate - Deluded by Dawkins?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... cause. A number of examples were discussed, mostly faith healings. Now, I believe that Andrew would agree that not all miracle claims are true, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2010/Dec/01/are-science-and-religion-incompatible/"&gt;Are Science and Religion Incompatible?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... that was rejected by science Most liberal religious faiths have tended to choose (2). The Catholic Church, for instance, has a pro-evolutiuon stance and ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Feb/11/book-review-unbelievable-by-justin-brierley/"&gt;Book Review - "Unbelievable?" by Justin Brierley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... pinpoint a 'moment of surrender' like mine, but their faith is nevertheless grounded in an experience of God's presence in their lives, perhaps in ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="science"></category><category term="statistics"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Dynamical systems with pyndamics</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Jan/14/dynamical-systems-with-pyndamics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-01-14:/posts/2019/Jan/14/dynamical-systems-with-pyndamics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Describe dynamical systems in terms of the differential equations without having to write the coding loops or functions.  Easily plot the changes in the variables, show phase plots, and vector …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Describe dynamical systems in terms of the differential equations without having to write the coding loops or functions.  Easily plot the changes in the variables, show phase plots, and vector fields.  Explore examples from modeling the zombie apocalypse, the infectiousness of ideas on Twitter, or the exchange of energy in the Earth climate system.  Useful for teaching dynamical systems for students with little programming experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Included is an interface to Bayesian MCMC with the emcee package for doing Bayesian parameter estimation and model comparison!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pyndamics" class="img-fluid" src="https://bblais.github.io/images/pyndamics.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pyndamics: Python Numerical Dynamics Simulator, &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/pyndamics"&gt;https://github.com/bblais/pyndamics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="presentations"&gt;Presentations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Twitter Zombies and the Fate of the World.pdf"&gt;Twitter, Zombies, and the Fate of the World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Mar 2017.  Analytics without Borders Conference.  &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/bblais/181abd99f878282666b98a29588dda41"&gt;Supplemental Notebook is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S. and Skaza, J., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/presentation Modeling the Infectiousness of Twitter Hashtags.pdf"&gt;Modeling the Infectiousness of Twitter Hashtags&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Sep 2016.  Bryant University Science Seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skaza, J. and Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/twitter-modeling-presentation.pdf"&gt;Mathematical Modeling of Trending Topics on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Apr 14, 2015.  Honors Capstone Presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witkowski, C. and Blais, B.S. Apr 2013.&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/zombies_presentation_apr2013.pdf"&gt;Zombie Apocalypse: An Epidemic Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; . Research and Engagment Day (REDay), Bryant University.&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/zombies_handout_apr2013.pdf"&gt;Supplemental Handout here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Blais, Colin Gannon, Qin Leng, Robert Patalano, Hong Yang. October 2013.&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/GSA%202013%20Poster.pdf"&gt;Bayesian Parameter Estimation in a 1D Model of Precipitation and Evaporation: Comparison of Middle Miocene and Modern Climates Using Plant Lipid Deuterium dD Measurements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Geological Society of America Conference. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/GSA%202013%20Poster%20Extra%20Slides.pdf"&gt;Some extra slides that didn't fit on the poster.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Space%20Grant%20Presentation%20Nov%202009.pdf"&gt;Modeling Ecosystems and Climates: A Teaching Simulator for Systems Dynamics&lt;/a&gt;* (Rhode Island Space Grant Consortium Annual Symposium, November 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="publications"&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skaza, J. and Blais, B.S. 2015. &lt;a href="http://authors.elsevier.com/a/1Tej31M2-1uo2K"&gt;Modeling the Infectiousness of Twitter Hashtags&lt;/a&gt;. Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications.  Volume 465, 1 January 2017, Pages 289–296.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witkowski, C. and Blais, B.S. 2013. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/2013-Witkowski.C;Blais.B-Bayesian%20Analysis%20of%20Epidemics%20-%20Zombies,%20Influenza,%20and%20other%20Diseases-..pdf"&gt;Bayesian analysis of epidemics - zombies, influenza, and other diseases&lt;/a&gt; . Available from the arXiv at &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1311.6376"&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1311.6376&lt;/a&gt; as well as on &lt;a href="https://www.scienceopen.com/document/vid/f27e3030-6d86-4af2-83a6-6ec0a2798582"&gt;ScienceOpen&lt;/a&gt;.  An &lt;a href="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/urls/dl.dropbox.com/s/rm8xtwhacsxpa8g/Bayesian%20Analysis%20of%20Epidemics%20-%20Using%20Zombies%20to%20Teach.ipynb"&gt;iPython notebook&lt;/a&gt; with the simulations is available &lt;a href="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/urls/dl.dropbox.com/s/rm8xtwhacsxpa8g/Bayesian%20Analysis%20of%20Epidemics%20-%20Using%20Zombies%20to%20Teach.ipynb"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematical models of epidemic dynamics offer significant insight into predicting and controlling infectious diseases. The dynamics of a disease model generally follow a susceptible, infected, and recovered (SIR) model, with some standard modifications. In this paper, we extend the work of Munz et.al (2009) on the application of disease dynamics to the so-called ``zombie apocalypse'', and then apply the identical methods to influenza dynamics. Unlike Munz et.al (2009), we include data taken from specific depictions of zombies in popular culture films and apply Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods on improved dynamical representations of the system. To demonstrate the usefulness of this approach, beyond the entertaining example, we apply the identical methodology to Google Trend data on influenza to establish infection and recovery rates. Finally, we discuss the use of the methods to explore hypothetical intervention policies regarding disease outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="science"></category><category term="dynamical systems"></category><category term="sie"></category></entry><entry><title>Models of Learning and Memory</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Jan/14/models-of-learning-and-memory/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-01-14:/posts/2019/Jan/14/models-of-learning-and-memory/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Simulate biologically derived neural networks of medium complexity - both rate- and spike-based models.  Explore the dynamics of synaptic plasticity under different input environments, including low-dimensional vector environments and natural image …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Simulate biologically derived neural networks of medium complexity - both rate- and spike-based models.  Explore the dynamics of synaptic plasticity under different input environments, including low-dimensional vector environments and natural image inputs.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Plasticnet"&gt;plasticnet + splikes:  synaptic modification in rate and spike-based neurons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims at providing a simple-to-use neural simulator at a medium-level of complexity. This package combines both rate and spike-based models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/plasticity"&gt;plasticity: synaptic modification in rate-based neurons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plasticity is a package with a convenient interface, used to run simulations of single cells and networks of neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B0pJ77HPErGWM2xraE91SGF1RkE/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;Natural Images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a collection of natural images used in my research. It contains the original images, scripts for processing the images, as well as scripts to download some of the standard databases, such as the Olshausen and VanHateren image databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="presentations"&gt;Presentations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S. Feb 2013.&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Physics%20Neuroscience%20Talk%20Feb%202013.pdf"&gt;From Theory to Experiment and Back Again: A Physicists Journey Through Neuroscience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; . University of Rhode Island Neuroscience Colloquium. (a keynote version, which includes the animations, is &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Physics%20Neuroscience%20Talk%20Feb%202013.zip"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/ICCNS%202008%20final.pdf"&gt;A Hierarchical Spatiotemporal Model of Neocortex With Probabilistic Feedback.&lt;/a&gt; (Twelfth International Conference on Cognitive and Neural Systems (ICCNS), May 2008)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Inhibition.pdf"&gt;Notes on Inhibition and BCM&lt;/a&gt; . (IBNS Research Meeting, April 2008)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/bearlab_080207.pdf"&gt;TTX and BCM&lt;/a&gt; . (MIT Lab Presentation, August 2007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/brown_talk1105.pdf"&gt;Plasticity in the Brain: A Physicist's Perspective on Learning and Memory&lt;/a&gt; (Brown University, Frontiers in the Interaction Between Physics and Biology, November 2005)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/neuro05_poster.pdf"&gt;Synaptic Modification in Spiking-Rate Models: A Comparison between Learning in Spiking Neurons and Rate-Based Neuron Models&lt;/a&gt;* (Society for Neuroscience, Poster Presentation, November 2005) with Scott Kuindersma.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/iccns05_html/img0.html"&gt;The Role of Structure and Noise in the Mouse Visual System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (ICCNS, May 2005) with Mikhail Frenkel (MIT), Scott Kuindersma (Bryant University), and Mark Bear (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/pres_082704b.pdf"&gt;Simulations of Monocular Deprivation in Mouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (MIT Lab Presentation, August 2004) with Scott Kuindersma.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/071304.pdf"&gt;Simulations of Monocular Deprivation in Mouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Brown IBNS Presentation, July 2004) with Scott Kuindersma.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/brinposter2003.pdf"&gt;Visual System Development and Organization: Using Direction and Orientation Maps to Compare Theory and Experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Biomedical Research Infrastructure Network, Poster Presentation (BRIN), 2003) with Christian Latino.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/NIPS2002.pdf"&gt;Selectivity and Metaplasticity in a Unified Calcium-Dependent Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (NIPS 2002)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/brinposter_2002.pdf"&gt;Neural Architecture and the Mechanisms for Learning and Memory Storage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Biomedical Research Infrastructure Network (BRIN), Poster Presentation, 2002) with Maria Cuartas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/iccns/iccns.htm"&gt;The Formation of Orientation and Direction Selectivity Maps: Comparing Rules of Synaptic Modification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (ICCNS, May 2001)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/job_talk/index.htm"&gt;The Physics of the Brain: Towards and Understanding of Learning and Memory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Job Talk, Jan 2000)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="publications"&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B. S. 2014. &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/referenceworkentry/10.1007/978-1-4614-7320-6_360-2"&gt;Receptive Field modeling&lt;/a&gt; in  &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4614-7320-6"&gt;Encyclopedia of Computational Neuroscience&lt;/a&gt;,  edited  by  D.  Jaeger  and R. Jung (Springer New York, 2014) pp. 1-6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S, Cooper, L.N , and Shouval H.Z. 2008. &lt;a href="http://pre.aps.org/abstract/PRE/v80/i6/e061915"&gt;Effect of correlated lateral geniculate nucleus firing rates on predictions for monocular eye closure versus monocular retinal inactivation&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Physical Review E&lt;/em&gt; 80 (6): 061915.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monocular deprivation experiments can be used to distinguish between different ideas concerning properties of cortical synaptic plasticity. Monocular deprivation by lid suture causes a rapid disconnection of the deprived eye connected to cortical neurons whereas total inactivation of the deprived eye produces much less of an ocular dominance shift. In order to understand these results one needs to know how lid suture and retinal inactivation affect neurons in the lateral geniculate nucleus (LGN) that provide the cortical input. Recent experimental results by Linden et al. showed that monocular lid suture and monocular inactivation do not change the mean firing rates of LGN neurons but that lid suture reduces correlations between adjacent neurons whereas monocular inactivation leads to correlated firing. These, somewhat surprising, results contradict assumptions that have been made to explain the outcomes of different monocular deprivation protocols. Based on these experimental results we modify our assumptions about inputs to cortex during different deprivation protocols and show their implications when combined with different cortical plasticity rules. Using theoretical analysis, random matrix theory and simulations we show that high levels of correlations reduce the ocular dominance shift in learning rules that depend on homosynaptic depression (i.e., Bienenstock-Cooper-Munro type rules), consistent with experimental results, but have the opposite effect in rules that depend on heterosynaptic depression (i.e., Hebbian/principal component analysis type rules).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S, Frenkel M. , Kuindersma S., Muhammad R., Shouval H.Z, Cooper, L.N , and Bear M. F. 2008 &lt;a href="https://www.physiology.org/doi/10.1152/jn.90411.2008"&gt;Recovery from monocular deprivation using binocular deprivation: Experimental observations and theoretical analysis&lt;/a&gt; . &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neurophysiology&lt;/em&gt; 100:2217-2224.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ocular dominance (OD) plasticity is a robust paradigm for examining the functional consequences of synaptic plasticity. Previous experimental and theoretical results have shown that OD plasticity can be accounted for by known synaptic plasticity mechanisms, using the assumption that deprivation by lid suture eliminates spatial structure in the deprived channel. Here we show that in the mouse, recovery from monocular lid suture can be obtained by subsequent binocular lid suture but not by dark rearing. This poses a significant challenge to previous theoretical results. We therefore performed simulations with a natural input environment appropriate for mouse visual cortex. In contrast to previous work we assume that lid suture causes degradation but not elimination of spatial structure, whereas dark rearing produces elimination of spatial structure. We present experimental evidence that supports this assumption, measuring responses through sutured lids in the mouse. The change in assumptions about the input environment is sufficient to account for new experimental observations, while still accounting for previous experimental results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blais, B.S. and Cooper, L.N 2008. &lt;a href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/BCM_theory"&gt;BCM Theory&lt;/a&gt; . &lt;em&gt;Scholarpedia&lt;/em&gt; 3(3):1570.&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BCM (Bienenstock et al., 1982) refers to the theory of synaptic modification first proposed by Elie Bienenstock, Leon Cooper, and Paul Munro in 1982 to account for experiments measuring the selectivity of neurons in primary sensory [8]cortex and its dependency on neuronal input. It is characterized by a rule expressing synaptic change as a Hebb-like product of the presynaptic activity and a nonlinear function, \phi(y;\theta_M) , of postsynatic activity, y. For low values of the postsynaptic activity ( y&amp;lt;\theta_M ), \phi is negative; for y&amp;gt;\theta_M , \phi is positive. The rule is stabilized by allowing the modification threshold, \theta_M , to vary as a super-linear function of the previous activity of the cell. Unlike traditional methods of stabilizing Hebbian learning, this "sliding threshold" provides a mechanism for incoming patterns, as opposed to converging afferents, to compete. A detailed exploration can be found in the book Theory of Cortical Plasticity (Cooper et al., 2004). For an open-source implementation of the BCM, amongst other synaptic modification rules, see the Plasticity package&lt;a href="http://plasticity.googlecode.com/"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shouval, H.Z, Gavornik, J. P., Shuler, M., Bear, M. F., and Blais, B.S. 2007. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/CRCNS07.pdf"&gt;Learning Reward Timing using Reinforced Expression of Synaptic Plasticity&lt;/a&gt;  In &lt;em&gt;Collaborative Research in Computational Neuroscience (CRCNS) Conference&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our collaborative research proposes to study the synaptic and cellular basis of receptive field plasticity in visual cortex. Recently some of our efforts have concentrated on accounting for novel aspects of cellular responses and plasticity observed in the visual cortex of the rat. In recently published findings we provided evidence that pairing visual cues with subsequent rewards in awake behaving animals results in the emergence, in the primary visual cortex (V1), of reward-timing activity (Shuler and Bear, 2006). Further, the properties of reward-timing activity suggest that it is generated locally within V1, implying that V1 is privy to a signal relating the acquisition of reward. We provide here a model demonstrating how such interval timing of reward could emerge in V1. A fundamental assumption of this work is that the timing characteristics of the V1 network are encoded in the lateral connectivity within the network, consequently the plasticity assumed in this model is of these recurrent connections. Using this assumption, no prior stimulus-locked temporal representation is necessary. The plasticity of recurrent connections is implemented through an interaction between an activity dependent Hebbian like plasticity, and a neuromodulatory signal signifying reward. It is demonstrated that such a global reinforcement signal is sufficient for interval time learning by stabilizing changes in nascent synaptic efficacy resultant from prior visually-evoked activity. By modifying synaptic weight change within the recurrent network of V1, our model transforms temporally restricted visual events into neurally persistent activity relating to their associated reward timing expectancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shouval, H.Z, Bear, M.F., and Blais, B.S. 2006. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/CRCNS_2006.pdf"&gt;The cellular basis of receptive field plasticity in visual cortex, an integrative experimental and theoretical approach&lt;/a&gt; . In &lt;em&gt;Collaborative Research in Computational Neuroscience (CRCNS) Conference&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Synaptic plasticity is a likely basis for information storage by the neocortex. Understanding cortical plasticity requires coordinated investigation of both underlying cellular mechanisms and their systems-level consequences in the same model system. However, establishing connections between the cellular and system levels of description is non-trivial. A major contribution of theoretical neuroscience is that it can link different levels of description, and in doing so can direct experiments to the questions of greatest relevance. The objective of the current project is to generate a theoretical description of experience-dependent plasticity in the rodent visual system. The advantages of rodents are, first, that knowledge of the molecular mechanisms of synaptic plasticity is relatively mature and continues to be advanced with genetic and pharmacological experiments, and second, rodents show robust receptive field plasticity in visual cortex (VC) that can be easily and inexpensively monitored with chronic recording methods. The project aims are threefold. First, the activity of inputs to rat visual cortex will be recorded in different viewing conditions that induce receptive field (RF) plasticity, and these data will be integrated into formal models of synaptic plasticity. Second, the dynamics of RF plasticity will be simulated using existing spike rate-based algorithms and compared will experimental observations. Third, the consequences of new biophysically plausible plasticity algorithms, based on spike timing and metaplasticity, will be analyzed and compared with experiments.6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S. and Kuindersma, S. 2005. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/neuro05_poster.pdf"&gt;Synaptic Modification in Spiking-Rate Models: A Comparison between Learning in Spiking Neurons and Rate-Based Neuron Models&lt;/a&gt;  In &lt;em&gt;Society For Neuroscience Conference Abstracts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rate-based neuron models have been successful in understanding many aspects of development such as the development of orientation selectivity(Bienenstock et al., 1982; Oja, 1982; Linsker, 1986; Miller, 1992; Bell and Sejnowski, 1997), the particular dynamics of visual deprivation(Blais et al., 1999) and the development of direction selectivity(Wimbauer et al., 1997; Blais et al., 2000). These models do not address phenomena such as temporal coding, spike-timing dependant synaptic plasticity, or any short-time behavior of neurons. More detailed spiking models (Song et.al, 2000; Shouval et.al. 2002; Yeung et.al. 2004) address these issues, and have had some success, but have failed to develop receptive fields in natural environments. These more detailed models are diffiult to explore, given their large number of parameters and the run-time computational limitations. In addition, their results are often diffiult to compare directly with the rate-based models. &lt;p&gt;We propose a model, which we call a spiking-rate model, which can serve as a middle-ground between the over simplistic rate-based models, and the more detailed spiking models. The spiking-rate model is a spiking model where all of the underlying processes are continuous Poisson, the summation of inputs is entirely linear (although non-linearities can be added), and the generation of outputs is done by calculating a rate output and then generating an appropriate Poisson spike train. In this way, the limiting behavior is identical to a rate-based model, but the proper ties of spiking models can be incorporated more easily. We present the development of receptive i!elds with this model in various visual environments. We then present the necessary conditions for the receptive field development in the spiking-rate models, and make comparisons to detailed spiking models, in order to more clearly understand the necessary conditions for receptive field development&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeung, L.C., Shouval, H.Z, Blais, B.S., Cooper, L. N. 2004. &lt;a href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/full/101/41/14943"&gt;Synaptic Homeostasis and Input Selectivity Follow From a Calcium-Dependent Plasticity Model&lt;/a&gt; . &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Science&lt;/i&gt;. Vol 101, Issue 41. 14943-14948.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifications in the strengths of synapses are thought to underlie memory, learning, and development of cortical circuits. Many cellular mechanisms of synaptic plasticity have been investigated in which differential elevations of postsynaptic calcium concentrations play a key role in determining the direction and magnitude of synaptic changes. We have previously described a model of plasticity that uses calcium currents mediated by N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors as the associative signal for Hebbian learning. However, this model is not completely stable. Here, we propose a mechanism of stabilization through homeostatic regulation of intracellular calcium levels. With this model, synapses are stable and exhibit properties such as those observed in metaplasticity and synaptic scaling. In addition, the model displays synaptic competition, allowing structures to emerge in the synaptic space that reflect the statistical properties of the inputs. Therefore, the combination of a fast calcium-dependent learning and a slow stabilization mechanism can account for both the formation of selective receptive fields and the maintenance of neural circuits in a state of equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cooper, L. N, Intrator, N., Blais, B.S., Shouval, H. Z. 2004. &lt;a href="plasticity/book.html"&gt;Theory of Cortical Plasticity&lt;/a&gt; . World Scientific Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This invaluable book presents a theory of cortical plasticity and shows how this theory leads to experiments that test both its assumptions and consequences. It ellucidates, in a manner that is accessible to students as well as researchers, the role which the BCM theory has played in guiding research and suggesting experiments that have led to our present understanding of the mechanisms underlying cortical plasticity. Most of the connections betwen theory and experiment that are discussed require complex simulations. A unique feature of the book is the accompanying software package, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="plasticity/index.html"&gt;Plasticity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;. This is provided complete with source code, and enables the reader to repeat any of the simulations quoted in the book as well as to vary either parameters or assumptions. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="plasticity/index.html"&gt;Plasticity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt; is thus a research and an educational tool. Readers can use it to obtain hands-on knowledge of the structure of BCM and various other learning algorithms. They can check and replicate our results as well as test algorithms and refinements of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="science"></category><category term="neuroscience"></category></entry><entry><title>Stats for Everyone</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Jan/14/stats-for-everyone/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-01-14:/posts/2019/Jan/14/stats-for-everyone/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have a statistics question or project?  I'd love to hear from you!  One of my goals is to bring statistical reasoning to everyone, both as a general framework for rational …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have a statistics question or project?  I'd love to hear from you!  One of my goals is to bring statistical reasoning to everyone, both as a general framework for rational thinking but also for specific uses in the arts and sciences.  I wrote a book, which I &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Statistical-Inference-for-Everyone"&gt;post for free&lt;/a&gt; but is also &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Statistical-Inference-Everyone-Brian-Blais/dp/1499715072"&gt;available on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, which presents a unique path through an introductory statistics class.  I also write tools to help researchers apply statistical techniques to their data and their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-book-for-free"&gt;The Book - for free!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Statistical-Inference-for-Everyone"&gt;latest version of the book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The print book is &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Statistical-Inference-Everyone-Brian-Blais/dp/1499715072"&gt;available on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, or directly [on Createspace]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Statistical-Inference-for-Everyone/tree/master/python"&gt;latest version of the software&lt;/a&gt;.  It requires the installation of a scientific distribution of Python, such as the &lt;a href="https://store.continuum.io/cshop/anaconda/"&gt;Anaconda distribution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tools"&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="files/Quantity.py"&gt;Quantity.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple class for doing Monte Carlo error analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="presentations"&gt;Presentations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3xAb3aVGVM0&amp;amp;t=2s"&gt;Your Lack of Imagination Can Kill You — But You Can Be Saved by Math&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Feb 2018.  TEDxBryantU.  Full &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/TEDxTalks/search?query=TEDxBryantU"&gt;list of videos for the event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=chwyqhgCz9s"&gt;Beginning with Bayes or Statistical Inference for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  May 2016. Electronic Conference On Teaching Statistics (eCOTS) 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-heresies-the-movie.html"&gt;seminar I give outlining the motivation and philosophy of the book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/rationality.pdf"&gt;Statistical Inference for Everyone: One Scientist's Attempt to Set the Record Straight on Rational Thought&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Mar 2015.  The Department of Science and Technology Seminar Series at Bryant University. You can download the &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie.html"&gt;current textbook here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S., &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Science_Probability_and_Models_of_the_World.pdf"&gt;Science, Probability, and Models of the World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  Aug 2015.  Presentation to China University of Geosciences Summer Exchange Trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Skaza and Brian Blais.  Mar 2014. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/IPE%20Conference%20March%202014.pdf"&gt;The Relationship between Economic Growth
and Environmental Degradation: Exploring Models and Questioning the Existence of an Environmental Kuznets Curve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. 21st Annual Conference Issues in Political Economy, Undergraduate Student Research in Economics.  See supporting paper at &lt;a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2346173"&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2346173&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blais, B.S. Mar 2013.&lt;em&gt; &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/Analytics_2013.pdf"&gt;Science and Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; . Analytics Symposium, Bryant University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/pres_011407.pdf"&gt;Teaching Bayesian Model Comparison with the Three-sided Coin.&lt;/a&gt; with Scott Kuindersma (UMass Amherst). (Bryant University Faculty Research Day, January 2007).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/pres_101205.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Determining the Geometry of a Three-sided Fair Coin: Exploring the Probability of a Coin Landing on its Edge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Brown University IBNS Lab Presentation, October 2005)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="publications"&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witkowski, C. R., Weijers, J. W. H. , Blais, B.S., Schouten, S., and Damsté, J. S. S. &lt;a href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/4/11/eaat4556"&gt;Molecular fossils from phytoplankton reveal secular pCO&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(_2\)&lt;/span&gt; trend over the Phanerozoic&lt;/a&gt;. Science Advances. Vol. 4, no. 11, eaat4556.  DOI: 10.1126/sciadv.aat4556.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skaza, J. and Blais, B.S. 2013. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/SSRN-id2346173.pdf"&gt;The Relationship between Economic Growth and Environmental Degradation: Exploring Models and Questioning the Existence of an Environmental Kuznets Curve&lt;/a&gt; . Available from: &lt;a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2346173"&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2346173&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://intranet.bryant.edu/portal/economic-studies/publications/working-papers.htm"&gt;http://intranet.bryant.edu/portal/economic-studies/publications/working-papers.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we explore a variety of models attempting to explain the pollution-income relationship (PIR). There has been much literature addressing the notion of an environmental Kuznets curve (EKC). Many researchers find an EKC relationship for certain pollutants, while others do not find evidence of an EKC relationship. There is also literature formally critiquing the EKC. We employ cross-sectional, panel, and time-series analysis to add insight into the relationship between economic growth and environmental degradation, a research area that is far from consensual and that has practical implications. We ultimately find that the clearest case of an EKC effect in our study arises in the analysis of organic water pollution, while there is modest evidence suggesting an EKC effect with regard to CO2, NO, and methane. We also present ample evidence suggesting an anti-EKC effect for PM10. Our analysis causes us to question the existence of an EKC effect throughout the environment in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yang, H., Blais, B.S., Leng, Q. 2011. &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/pdf/2011_yang.pdf"&gt;Stable isotope variations from cultivated Metasequoia trees in the United States: A statistical approach to assess isotope signatures as climate signals.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Jpn. J. His tor. Bot.&lt;/em&gt; 19 (1-2) pp 75-88.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We measured I'C and I'15N values and carbon and nitrogen elemental concentrations of leaves collected from Metasequoia glyptostroboides Hu et Cheng trees cultivated at 39 sites across the United States under different latitudes and climatic regions. I'D values from south facing leaf n-alkanes of 27 trees were also determined. Climate data over the past 50 years (1950a2009) were compiled from stations near each site. Isotope data were cross plotted against each geographic and climatic parameter, including latitude, annual mean temperature (AMT), spring (FebruaryaMay) mean temperature (SMT), annual mean precipitation (AMP), and spring mean precipitation (SMP). Statistical analyses revealed the following signicant correlations: 1) a strong negative correlation between n-alkane D and latitude; 2) statistically signicant correlations between D and both AMT and SMT; 3) a weaker but still signicant correlation between I'D and SMP; 4) statistically signicant relationships between carbon concentration and both temperature and precipitation parameters, especially AMP; 5) an unexpected correlation between nitrogen concentration and SMP. These results bear strong implications for using I'13C and I'D values obtained from fossil Metasequoia as paleoclimatic and paleoenvironmental proxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuindersma, S.R. and Blais, B.S. 2007. &lt;a href="http://pubs.amstat.org/doi/abs/10.1198/000313007X222497"&gt;Teaching Bayesian Model Comparison With the Three-sided Coin&lt;/a&gt; . &lt;em&gt;American Statistician&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 61, No. 3, August 2007 pp.239-244&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present work we introduce the problem of determining the probability that a rotating and bouncing cylinder (i.e. flipped coin) will land and come to rest on its edge. We present this problem and analysis as a practical, nontrivial example to introduce the reader to Bayesian model comparison. Several models are presented, each of which take into consideration different physical aspects of the problem and the relative effects on the edge landing probability. The Bayesian formulation of model comparison is then used to compare the models and their predictive agreement with data from hand-flipped cylinders of several sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="science"></category><category term="statistics"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="sie"></category></entry><entry><title>Statistical Inference for Everyone (sie)</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Nov/21/statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-11-21:/posts/2014/Nov/21/statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Dice.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 250px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a new approach to an introductory statistical inference textbook, motivated by probability theory as logic.  It is targeted to the typical &lt;em&gt;Statistics 101&lt;/em&gt; college student, and covers the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Dice.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 250px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a new approach to an introductory statistical inference textbook, motivated by probability theory as logic.  It is targeted to the typical &lt;em&gt;Statistics 101&lt;/em&gt; college student, and covers the topics typically covered in the first semester of such a course.  It is freely available under the Creative Commons License, and includes a software library in Python for making some of the calculations and visualizations easier.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="get-the-book"&gt;Get the book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Statistical-Inference-for-Everyone"&gt;latest version of the book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The print book is &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Statistical-Inference-Everyone-Brian-Blais/dp/1499715072"&gt;available on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, or directly &lt;a href="https://www.createspace.com/4808244"&gt;on Createspace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="https://github.com/bblais/Statistical-Inference-for-Everyone/tree/master/python"&gt;latest version of the software&lt;/a&gt;.  It requires the installation of a scientific distribution of Python, such as the &lt;a href="https://store.continuum.io/cshop/anaconda/"&gt;Anaconda distribution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="in-the-movies"&gt;In the movies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch the &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-heresies-the-movie.html"&gt;seminar I give outlining the motivation and philosophy of the book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch the &lt;a href="https://www.causeweb.org/cause/ecots/ecots16"&gt;eCOTS 2016&lt;/a&gt; poster &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/chwyqhgCz9s"&gt;presentation that I gave here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="more-info"&gt;More info&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instructors who want to see a more technical justification for this approach, you can see a &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/github/bblais/Tech-SIE/blob/master/Prologue/Prologue.ipynb"&gt;technical supplement&lt;/a&gt; that I am putting together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestions or comments, please comment here, or email me directly!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="statistics"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="sie"></category></entry><entry><title>Pennies!</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/May/28/pennies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-05-28:/posts/2014/May/28/pennies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Pennies.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 250px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just added an example of simple model construction to my textbook, &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie.html"&gt;Statistical Inference for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;.  It's a process I don't think I've ever seen in an intro stats book …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Pennies.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 250px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just added an example of simple model construction to my textbook, &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie.html"&gt;Statistical Inference for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;.  It's a process I don't think I've ever seen in an intro stats book, but is common in scientific work.  The idea is that you start off with a simple model, collect data, then notice where your simple model breaks, propose a new more complex model, and do the analysis again.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire data set I use is here, where I have the mass of US Pennies for several years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mass&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.133&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1961&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.083&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1962&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.175&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1963&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.120&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1964&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1965&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.060&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1966&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1967&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1968&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.073&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1969&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.076&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1971&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.110&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1972&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.080&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1973&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1974&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.093&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1990&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1991&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1993&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.503&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.497&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1997&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.494&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1998&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.512&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1999&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.521&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.523&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.520&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id="single-true-value-model"&gt;Single "True" Value Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One starts this analysis loading the first part (earlier than 1975), and applying a model which states that there is a single "true" value.  The best estimate of this value is the sample mean, and the posterior distribution is normal.  A plot of this looks like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="single" src="images/mass1965_1974_1_value.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you apply it to all the data, you get something that clearly looks ridiculous:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="single2" src="images/mass1965_2003_1_value.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is then that it makes sense to change the model to a two "true" values model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="double-true-value-model"&gt;Double "True" Value Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this model, we have separate means for the pre- and post-1975 data, and can look at the overlap of the credible intervals, or the posterior distribution of the difference, both of which clearly show a statistically significant difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="double" src="images/mass1965_2003_2_value.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="double diff" src="images/mass1965_2003_2_value_diff.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="advantages"&gt;Advantages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has several advantages over the typically methods used to teach this topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it progresses systematically from simple to complex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it shows the benefits and limitations of the simple models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it connects the procedures of the complex models to the earlier ones, so they don't seem like disjoint unrelated topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="statistics"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="sie"></category></entry><entry><title>The Cover Art for Statistical Inference for Everyone (sie)</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2014/Jan/15/the-cover-art-for-statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2014-01-15:/posts/2014/Jan/15/the-cover-art-for-statistical-inference-for-everyone-sie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p align='center'&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Dice.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 500px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover art for my book, &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-inference-for-everyone.html"&gt;Statistical Inference for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;, is something created by me and I'd like to explain my design.  We have a picture of &lt;a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap131113.html"&gt;Saturn&lt;/a&gt;, taken by …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p align='center'&gt;&lt;img src="images/Saturn_with_Dice.png" alt="SIE" style="width: 500px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover art for my book, &lt;a href="http://web.bryant.edu/~bblais/statistical-inference-for-everyone.html"&gt;Statistical Inference for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;, is something created by me and I'd like to explain my design.  We have a picture of &lt;a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap131113.html"&gt;Saturn&lt;/a&gt;, taken by the &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/cassini/main/"&gt;NASA Cassini Mission&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;em&gt;moons&lt;/em&gt; orbiting around replaced by dice.  This is a nod to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre-Simon_Laplace"&gt;Laplace&lt;/a&gt; who used the sorts of analysis presented in this book and applied it to calculating the mass of Saturn.  The point of the dice is to remind us that all of this analysis started in the determination of the chances of winning various games of gambling, and that all statistical inference derives from those basic principles.  We start by an analysis of dice rolling, and as a consequence can estimate the mass of Saturn and explore many other properties of the Universe.  Probability is everything!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="statistics"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="sie"></category></entry></feed>