<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - religion</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/religion.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Skepticism and Dubious Medical Procedures</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2020/Jul/09/skepticism-and-dubious-medical-procedures/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2020-07-09:/posts/2020/Jul/09/skepticism-and-dubious-medical-procedures/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my discussion with Jonathan McLatchie on the Still Unbelievable podcast, I said that there hasn’t been a verified miracle claim even since Hume’s essay on miracles.  Here I look into the papers he references in response.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2020/May/29/jonathan-and-brian-in-conversation/"&gt;discussion with Jonathan McLatchie on the Still Unbelievable podcast&lt;/a&gt;, I said that there hasn’t been a verified miracle claim even since Hume’s essay on miracles.  Jonathan then told me two: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Case report of instantaneous resolution of juvenile macular degeneration blindness after proximal intercessory prayer”, Clarissa Romez, Kenn Freedman, David Zaritzky, Joshua W. Brown. &lt;em&gt;Explore&lt;/em&gt;. Available online 28 February 2020 &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550830720300926"&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550830720300926&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Case Report of gastroparesis healing: 16 years of a chronic syndrome resolved after proximal intercessory prayer”,Clarissa Romeza, David Zaritzky, Joshua W. Brown. &lt;em&gt;Complementary Therapies in Medicine&lt;/em&gt;. Volume 43, April 2019, Pages 289-294.  &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0965229918313116"&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0965229918313116&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when I looked at this, I kept finding those two and a third, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Study of the Therapeutic Effects of Proximal Intercessory Prayer (STEPP) on Auditory and Visual Impairments in Rural Mozambique”, Candy Gunther Brown, Stephen C Mory, Rebecca Williams, Michael J McClymond.  &lt;em&gt;South Med J&lt;/em&gt;. 2010 Sep;103(9):864-9 &lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20686441/"&gt;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20686441/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three kept popping up again and again.  The journals have dubious standards, and the authors work for the same institution (&lt;a href="https://www.globalmri.org/about"&gt;https://www.globalmri.org/about&lt;/a&gt;).  On their website there is the following request: “We’re always looking for new testimonies. Do you have a testimony that is medically verified?”.  Could you imagine a similar claim written about, say, a homeopathic remedy for cancer?  If you took our remedy, and improved, we want to hear from you.  Otherwise, not.  Regardless of the contents of the specific studies, this sort of fishing for positive results is thoroughly unscientific and casts significant doubt on any results from this institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suspicions were confirmed going to &lt;a href="http://sciencebasedmedicine.org"&gt;http://sciencebasedmedicine.org&lt;/a&gt; (a great resource) where they have an article about the 3rd study in the list above:  &lt;a href="https://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/proximal-intercessory-prayer/"&gt;https://theness.com/neurologicablog/index.php/proximal-intercessory-prayer/&lt;/a&gt;  Bottom line, this study has numerous, basic scientific problems with it and the results cannot be trusted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that argument that a deity is better able to heal when the person asking them to do so is physically close to the person they are praying for absurd, lame, and convenient. It is a nice excuse to unblind the protocol, and nothing else –  a way of generating false-positive results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the process for collecting subjects used by these authors and supported by their institution,  in addition to their experimental design, is constructed with the sole purpose of bypassing the methods of science.  I was particularly surprised when I dug into the first study, went into their supplemental information, and saw a nice timeline of events (&lt;strong&gt;emphasis mine&lt;/strong&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[…]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 14 1960  Complete Neurological Examination Completely normal except for macular degeneration “cause undetermined”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1971 Examination confirms “ legal blindness” Recording of Visual Acuities - are consistent with legal blindness. No glasses recommended.  Degeneration and scaring (sic) of macula in both eyes &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1971-1974 Record of a series of Visual Acuities Visual Acuities consistent with legal blindness until record of 1974  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/29/71  Visual Acuity  Right Eye- Finger Count  Left Eye - Hand motion- All without glasses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-18-72  Right Eye - Hand Motion,  Left Eye - Hand Motion &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6-14-74 Right Eye - 20/100-1 Left Eye - 20/100-2  All (above) without glasses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1972 Learned to use a cane and read braille.  Blind Services: orientation and mobility skills and braille reading  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02/18/1972-05/18/1972: Patient reports going through a Training Center to learn to walk with a cane and read braille. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1972   August Vision restored through PIP &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 4, 2001 Complete Eye Examination&lt;/strong&gt; VA 20/40 OD, 20/40-2 OS Corrected VA 20/40 OU None recorded Visual Acuity 20/40, 20/40-2.  Glasses -0.25 OD, -0.50 OS Normal eye exam except for evidence of dry eye early cataract changes. Optic nerves and maculae recorded as normal but also states + RPE dropout in macula OU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October 16, 2001  Return Visit. Treatment for Dry Eyes Provided&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October 3, 2012.  Cataract surgery of right eye&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the time between the prayer and the eye exam is…29 years!  This is “instantaneous resolution”?  Essentially, we’re taking this patient's word that their eyesight improved after prayer, but the authors (or anyone else) didn’t bother to test it for nearly 30 years.  This level of incompetence, poor design, and digging for positive results is staggering.  This is not the way one confirms medical claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second study seems at least a bit better, but with no controls, and knowing that the authors have a history of ludicrously bad design leaves me unconvinced.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I have tried to convey here is the process for investigating claims.  You look at the originals, you examine methods and possible ways the authors could have (deliberately or not) biased the results.  This is why we have blinding processes for medical experiments, and controls.  Otherwise you can always fall victim to false positives and rare one-off events.  We know that medical conditions can mysteriously improve (biology is complex and not entirely understood), so if you want to show your method of treatment actually works you do need to follow reasonable, skeptical procedures established by science.  It's certainly hard to do this, takes more time and work, but there is good reason why we trust science.  The lazy procedures of these authors -- including a self-proclaimed fishing for positive results -- is at best a cop-out and at worst a dishonest attempt to peddle bogus treatments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Probability of the Resurrection</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Sep/03/probability-of-the-resurrection/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-09-03:/posts/2019/Sep/03/probability-of-the-resurrection/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a recent discussion about the use of probability in a religious context I saw another poor job of a calculation of the Resurrection (I had read several others that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a recent discussion about the use of probability in a religious context I saw another poor job of a calculation of the Resurrection (I had read several others that had serious problems).  I then felt that it would be good to sketch out how it &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be done.  The goal here is not to come up with a single number, but to have a structure which invites discussion.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-smaller-problem"&gt;A smaller problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are restricting the problem to the smallest possible case to most easily see the form that the calculation takes when done properly.  The problem is &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of yours flipped a coin three times and got heads three times in a row.  Would this be good evidence for your friend having a coin with two heads compared to, say, a typical coin with 1 heads and 1 tails?  Here we have 2 models (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, say, is for the 1-headed coin model and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M_2\)&lt;/span&gt; is for the 2-headed coin model), and some observed data (heads, heads, heads in 3 flips).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to know the probability of each of the models given the data.  In math notation we use the vertical bar,&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|\)&lt;/span&gt;, as the symbol for "given".  The "data" is summarized as "H H H" for three observed heads flips.  So we want to obtain,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
P(M_1 | \text{H H H})  \text{ and } P(M_2 | \text{H H H})
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
following Bayes theorem, we write the top of Bayes equation as 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
P(M_1 | \text{H H H}) \sim P(\text{H H H}| M_1) \times P(M_1)
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
P(M_2 | \text{H H H}) \sim P(\text{H H H}| M_2) \times P(M_2)
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before continuing, let me point out a few things.  First, I'm not using equals here, but the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sim\)&lt;/span&gt; sign to denote that I'm writing just the top part of the equation first.  I'll add these two things up to get the bottom of Bayes in the next step.  I do it as a two-step process to make it easier to write down (i.e. it formats better in text) and to help when we generalize to more than 2 models, where Bayes can get a bit unwieldy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{H H H}| M_1)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the probability we'd see the data if we knew (i.e. we're given) that model 1 is true.  Since &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M_1\)&lt;/span&gt; is from a fair coin, we get 1/2 probability for each head independently and we don't have any extra counting term, so we'd get the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{H H H}| M_1)=\frac{1}{2}\times\frac{1}{2}\times\frac{1}{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The term &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{H H H}| M_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the probability we'd see the data if we knew (i.e. we're given) that model 2 is true.  Since &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M_2\)&lt;/span&gt; is from a rigged two-headed coin, we get a probability of 1 for each head so we'd get the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{H H H}| M_2)=1\times 1\times 1\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terms &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M_1)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; are the prior probabilities of the model - how much we should believe them before we saw the data.  This is probably the most contentious point, and worth dwelling on.  It's not 50%, just because there are two possibilities.  Do we even know if a two-headed coin exists?  Have you ever seen one?  The two models are not symmetric.  Turns out I have seen one!  There's one in my desk, which I love to bring out to fool my students.  :-)  It was found by accident with my daughter going through all of our loose change.  I have never seen one since, but if we just took my house as an example, it's no bigger than a 1/100 of all the quarters.  This can inform the prior as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M_1) = 0.99\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M_2) = 0.01\)&lt;/span&gt;.  I would guess that this is a huge &lt;em&gt;over estimate&lt;/em&gt; for the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; but it's good to run with.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting back to our probabilities, we calculate the top terms of Bayes, add them up, and then go back to divide each by that total.  Thus we get:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
\begin{align}
P(M_1 | \text{H H H}) &amp;amp;\sim P(\text{H H H}| M_1) \times P(M_1) = \frac{1}{2}\times\frac{1}{2}\times\frac{1}{2}\times 0.99 = 0.124 \\
P(M_2 | \text{H H H}) &amp;amp;\sim P(\text{H H H}| M_2) \times P(M_2) = 1\times 1\times 1\times 0.01 = 0.01
\end{align}
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(adding them up) &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T=0.124 + 0.01 = 0.134\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;finally getting (notice the equals now)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
\begin{align}
P(M_1 | \text{H H H}) &amp;amp;=0.124/T = 0.124/0.134=0.925 \\
P(M_2 | \text{H H H}) &amp;amp;=0.01/T=0.01/0.134 = 0.075
\end{align}
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, finally, we can have good reason -- by a long shot -- to &lt;em&gt;not believe&lt;/em&gt; that the person has a 2-headed coin.   Although we  have a nearly &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(8\times\)&lt;/span&gt; increase in the probability of that model, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, given the observed data of 3 heads, this doesn't bring our confidence up to the level of belief - you'd need more data for that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem has exactly the same structure as the problem under consideration, trying to find the probability of the resurrection given the data we have and the number of possible models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-problem-at-hand-the-probability-of-the-resurrection"&gt;The problem at hand - the probability of the Resurrection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proper way to set the problem up, like the coin, is the following.  First, we start with the different models:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; = Resurrection happened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; = Resurrection story made up entirely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(V\)&lt;/span&gt; = Resurrection story incited by visions from early apostles and embellished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and then the math follows just like the example above,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;data = texts of gospels and Paul (and their history)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R | \text{data}) \sim P(\text{data} | R) \times P(R)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M | \text{data}) \sim P(\text{data} | M) \times P(M)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(V | \text{data}) \sim P(\text{data} | V) \times P(V)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;.... [insert more models if you'd like]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then add up to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T = \ldots\)&lt;/span&gt;, and divide all terms, just like the coin.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments over priors can ensue, but I think it would  be fair to say that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(M)&amp;gt;P(V) \gg P(R)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Although one might question this order (e.g.  arguing that visions are more common than story construction) it is certainly true that resurrections are far less common than stories or visions.  How often do we see resurrections?  How often do we see God raising someone from the dead?  How often have we heard claims of people being raised from the dead, from God or otherwise?  These very simple questions bring the prior for the Resurrection &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; down.  The theist will typically counter with something like "I agree that resurrections through &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; processes are extremely unlikely, but if there is a God he could easily make resurrections through &lt;em&gt;supernatural&lt;/em&gt; causes likely."  I'll deal specifically with this objection in detail below but at this point the term &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R)\)&lt;/span&gt; doesn't presuppose any mechanisms - it is just the probability of a resurrection before seeing any data and it should be agreed that this is much lower than visions or stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the prior, we note that terms like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{data} | R)\)&lt;/span&gt; have to balance both the positive claims and negative claims.  For example, we might say that this term is quite high from the positive claims -- if the Resurrection actually happened then it easily explains the stories of seeing Jesus afterward.  However, there are things that we probably should have seen -- but don't -- if the Resurrection actually happened.  Some includes the lack of an account of Roman stolen-body litigation (as would have been done to the disciples), the fact that Paul doesn't mention the empty tomb, and the guards at the tomb are only mentioned in Matthew are not mentioned in Mark, Luke, John, or even Paul.  These negative claims are easily explained with the other two models but are not easily explained from the Resurrection model making &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\text{data} | R)\)&lt;/span&gt; much lower than is generally communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="supernatural-causation"&gt;Supernatural causation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what about the claim that the low priors are mitigated by the issue of God &lt;em&gt;supernaturally&lt;/em&gt; raising Jesus?  Here is where it gets interesting.  If you want to add the possibility of God raising Jesus &lt;em&gt;supernaturally&lt;/em&gt; from the dead we can do this with a process called &lt;em&gt;marginalization&lt;/em&gt;, which is a fancy term for adding up all of the possibilities.  Mathematically it looks like the following,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First define some symbols,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(+G\)&lt;/span&gt; = God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(+S\)&lt;/span&gt; = Supernatural action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-G\)&lt;/span&gt; = no God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-S\)&lt;/span&gt; = natural action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then draw out the probability terms (which don't mention any specific methods of resurrections) into several terms, each for a different method, and then apply Bayes' rule yielding
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$
\begin{align}
P(R | \text{data}) =&amp;amp; P(R, +G,+S | \text{data}) + P(R, -G,+S| \text{data}) + P(R, +G,-S| \text{data}) + P(R, -G,-S| \text{data})\\
\sim &amp;amp; P(\text{data}|R,+G,+S)P(R|+G,+S)P(+S|+G)P(+G) + \\ \nonumber
&amp;amp;P(\text{data}|R,-G,+S)P(R|-G,+S)P(+S|-G)P(-G) + \\ \nonumber
&amp;amp;P(\text{data}|R,+G,-S)P(R|+G,-S)P(-S|+G)P(+G) + \\ \nonumber
&amp;amp;P(\text{data}|R,-G,-S)P(R|-G,-S)P(-S|-G)P(-G) 
\end{align}
$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This messy result lets us look at individual terms to see where we might have to examine the data more closely.  Theists state that terms like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|-G,-S)\)&lt;/span&gt; are small (unlikely resurrection given no God and only natural action), and I'll grant you that.  How about &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P( R | +G, -S)\)&lt;/span&gt; or, in words,  why couldn't God have done the resurrection naturally?  How about  $P( R | -G, +S) $ or, in words, couldn't Satan or Stephen Fry's evil God have done the resurrection supernaturally?  How have theists ruled these out?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, by opening up some specific alternatives, one needs to follow all of those alternatives -- and their inverses -- through the entire calculation.  You then have to provide evidence for God's supposed actions (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(+S|+G)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(-S|+G)\)&lt;/span&gt;) reading his inscrutable plan.  You also have to demonstrate that there are not other supernatural agents at play, and that it is likely that God is the one acting. Given that theists have yet to provide &lt;em&gt;any way&lt;/em&gt; of testing supernatural claims &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; it seems like a big feat.  In short, by introducing supernatural causation into the mix, theists have made their life harder -- not easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Book Review - "Unbelievable?" by Justin Brierley</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2019/Feb/11/book-review-unbelievable-by-justin-brierley/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2019-02-11:/posts/2019/Feb/11/book-review-unbelievable-by-justin-brierley/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="structure-of-the-review"&gt;Structure of the Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I finished this review it became apparent that there are two main audiences for what I wrote - those that have yet to read the book …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="structure-of-the-review"&gt;Structure of the Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I finished this review it became apparent that there are two main audiences for what I wrote - those that have yet to read the book and those that have already read the book.  Therefore I decided to break the review up into two parts, one for each audience.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="for-those-that-have-not-yet-read-unbelievable"&gt;For those that have &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; yet read &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="context"&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been listening to &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable"&gt;this podcast&lt;/a&gt; for years and even had a &lt;a href="http://bblais.github.io/search.html?q=unbelievable"&gt;project several years ago&lt;/a&gt; with the lofty goal of responding to each and every episode.  I did not achieve the goal, unfortunately.  The problem was two-fold:
1. There are too many episodes
2. Nearly every episode is so packed with interesting content that my responses were taking longer than a week to prepare, so I was always behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast is a model of how discussions can go, even when the topic is contentious.  Justin Brierley is the epitome of civil.  Like a good moderator, it isn't always clear where he stands on the issue - it's even easy to ignore the fact that he's a believer himself!  He does an amazing job in the podcast of rephrasing what even his opponents state - skillfully  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man#Steelmanning"&gt;steelmanning&lt;/a&gt; the entire time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book, &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Unbelievable-the-Book"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unbelievable? Why After Ten Years of Talking with Atheists I'm Still a Christian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has all the best of the podcast in book form.  It's a plea for a return to civil discourse on hard topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Having conversations as one of the most important things we do in life“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Many conversation descend into the equivalent of verbal hand grenades being lobbed over the barricades of our carefully erected worldviews.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brierley demonstrates how you can respect a position that you disagree with and how you can -- without fear -- present someone else's argument even better than they can.  I can't help but think that this book was aptly timed for this age of quick sound-bites and tweets.  We live in a culture where it seems to be acceptable to malign your opponent without addressing their concerns or characterize their positions in such uncharitable ways that everyone speaks past each other.  It is a ray of light that this book - despite the fact that I disagree strongly with its conclusions - reaches across the aisle gently and respectfully with an invitation to engage in the discussion openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is for this reason, out of respect, that I take a thoughtful, thorough approach to this review.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="structure-of-the-book"&gt;Structure of the Book&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first chapter on &lt;em&gt;"Creating Better Conversations,"&lt;/em&gt; the book's chapters walk the reader through all of the standard arguments for God and Christianity, sprinkled with anecdotes from Brierley's interviews.  The book reads very nicely and has a conversational tone, introducing the reader to some of Brierley's original reasons for believing - from personal experience and revelation - and many other reasons to support which belief that he admits came later along.  The book is remarkably complete and as far as I can tell, hits all the major apologetics' points - including some arguments that have been circulating in the Christian community literally for thousands of years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brierley explains the Cosmological Arguments and the Fine Tuning Arguments in the chapter &lt;em&gt;"God Makes Sense of Human Existence."&lt;/em&gt;  The Moral Arguments, likewise, are addressed in the chapter &lt;em&gt;"God Makes Sense of Human Value."&lt;/em&gt;  He continues with arguments from purpose, the existence of Jesus, the evidence for the Resurrection, and suffering. Brierley finishes the book with a pragmatic explanation of living in the "Christian Story" and the benefits of choosing to live in that way.  For anyone not familiar with the standard arguments for Christianity, &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt; is a great introduction and summary of the primary arguments.  For anyone who cares about civil and intelligent dialog, this book is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="for-those-that-have-read-unbelievable"&gt;For those that have read &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I am not convinced by these arguments and Brierley is where is the divide?  I will hopefully address this question in the rest of this review.  I break each of my responses into the appropriate topics, essentially following the order of the book, discussing where I disagree with Brierley's conclusions at many places.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must admit that most of the chapters present so much of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; sides of the arguments that the book is unusually balanced for its genre.  It also means that this review is quite a bit longer than I would do for other books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-experience"&gt;Personal Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Brierley, by his own admission, personal experience is the primary reason for his &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; conversion.  He refers to a personal experience in a youth retreat in 1995, calling it a “moment of surrender“ where God "showed up," noting that most if not all Christians would probably relate to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I suspect that something similar is true for most people who call themselves Christians.  It's not that they can necessarily pinpoint a 'moment of surrender' like mine, but their faith is nevertheless grounded in an experience of God's presence in their lives, perhaps in some emotionally tangible way, or simply as a deep-down 'knowing' that has been there as long as they can remember." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never had such an experience, at least not tangibly, so I can't address Brierley's experience directly.  However, we have learned from science that personal experience that isn't accessible to others doesn't typically track reality - it tracks subjectivity.  People have profound experiences quite often and then interpret these experiences in all sorts of ways.  This does not mean that those interpretations are correct, even if the experiences themselves are real.  It is only through an honest exploration of the possible explanations, through prediction and skepticism, that we can achieve something close to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think Brierley would disagree with this - which is why he goes to great pains to explore the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="second-law-of-thermodynamics"&gt;Second Law of Thermodynamics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My dad also said something else. As a scientist he found it intriguing that the emergence of life on our planet seems to disobey one of the fundamental laws of nature. The Second Law of Thermodynamics states that, when left to their own devices, all closed systems (such as our universe), will move towards increasing 'entropy' -- the scientific word for disorder.“ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every physicist will tell you why this is an incorrect statement - because the earth is not a closed system.  Under the logic of this quote, even something like frozen ice would not be produced on the earth because it is a lower entropy state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had a bad experience with this particular argument in University.  The correction to the argument is both easy to find.  Further, unlike other such arguments, you won't find any disagreement with any physicist you ask.  It is the fact that the answer is so easy to find and consistent with the experts that there really is no excuse left to keep using this argument.  Even so, I have seen Christians use it &lt;em&gt;even after being corrected&lt;/em&gt;.  The claim is so outlandish, from a physical point of view, that if a scientist actually believed it, they would have to admit that a frozen pond (also a decrease in entropy) would be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim presented in this quote represents a pervasive lack of imagination on the part of the theist where they seemingly can't wrap their brains around the idea that complexity can arise from natural processes.  This lack of imagination infects not just this argument, but the fine tuning argument, other arguments from design, and even the moral argument. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fine-tuning"&gt;Fine Tuning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sean Carroll, an outspoken cosmologist from CalTech, says that &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X0qKZqPy9T8&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2305"&gt;the Fine Tuning Argument is the "theist's best argument"&lt;/a&gt; and it is well communicated in "&lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt;."  The problem is that, despite the confident claims of many theists, the physicists are not at all clear how much fine tuning there is or if there is any at all.  The way fine tuning is demonstrated starts with noticing that there are some &lt;em&gt;seemingly arbitrary&lt;/em&gt; constants in our physical laws (e.g. speed of light, expansion rate of the universe, etc...).  These constants if &lt;em&gt;varied independently&lt;/em&gt; lead to conditions where life &lt;em&gt;as we know it&lt;/em&gt;  couldn't form.  The emphasis here is to point out the problems with making confident claims about these observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the constants may be determined by other laws we don't know right now.  This has happened already for the expansion rate of the universe, which can be specifically derived from Einstein's equations - and shown to not be fine-tuned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the constants may not be independent, so changing one may necessitate changing another by a specific amount negating the effect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we don't understand the conditions &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these objections, it seems premature to make any strong statements about fine tuning even if you are convinced it is there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="something-out-of-nothing"&gt;Something out of nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is telling, I think, that the primary scientific arguments for God rely on the fringes of the known science into the unknown.  William Lane Craig makes a great deal out of the absurd notion of something "popping into existence" from nothing - and to allow even one instance of it would allow things like bicycles to appear out of nothing.  However, he doesn't address Sean Carroll directly who shows that models of the origin of the universe have some things able to appear out of nothing and other things not.  These models actually make &lt;em&gt;predictions&lt;/em&gt; for things we may observe, e.g. correlations in the microwave background, values of the early universe entropy, etc...  What &lt;em&gt;predictions&lt;/em&gt; do the theistic models actually make about the properties of the observable universe?  None to my knowledge.  It is clear that science and religion are playing by different rules here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contingent-vs-necessary"&gt;Contingent vs Necessary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brierley comments about the argument from contingency, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I've been struck by the obvious yet remarkable fact that there is &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; at all. [...]  Like Leibniz, I can see that it's perfectly logically possible that there could have been nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a philosopher and am unconvinced by words like &lt;em&gt;contingent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;.  For example, I do not see any support for the claim that there are &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; objects, or that a &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mind&lt;/em&gt; could satify the requirements to be &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;.  Maybe the only things that can be &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; are things like laws of logic, and that objects don't fit that criterion.  I don't know!  But until these are actually &lt;em&gt;demonstrated&lt;/em&gt; and not just &lt;em&gt;asserted&lt;/em&gt;, all of the arguments based on them have no content.  In the same way, perhaps the concept of "&lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;" isn't well defined and can't manifest in reality, so the question "why is there something rather than nothing" is answered simply with "because 'nothing' isn't realizable".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s nothing about our universe to suggest that it had to exist rather its existence is contingent. It needs an explanation of his existence.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would add as an analogy that there’s nothing about our experience on the Earth to suggest that the Earth is round or that it orbits the sun.  It may be &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt; possible to have a flat planet, but not &lt;em&gt;physically&lt;/em&gt; realizable in our universe (note: the spherical nature of planets is due to the spherical form of the law of gravitation).  Our intuitions do not always track the truth, and truth should be our goal.  As a scientist, I am accustomed to cases of seemingly obvious things being false, and of seemingly impossible things being true irrespective of our intuitions.  Thus, strictly &lt;em&gt;philosophical arguments&lt;/em&gt; are not enough to demonstrate the existence of something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="language-of-the-universe"&gt;Language of the Universe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is the universe written in the language of mathematics? Brierley says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who want to ask `Why?', atheism's only answer seems to be that it is a massive coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t see it as a coincidence I see it as a requirement. In &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; universe that has any patterns at all such that life could possibly exist - no matter what form of life - then those living beings would discover those patterns as the "mathematics" of that universe.  It doesn't surprise me that there are patterns in the universe, but I still agree with Brierley that it is an amazing thing that the universe exists at all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"So does science provide iron-clad proof for God's existence? No.  Could the scientific consensus change in the future?  Of course it could.  Is this all there is to say on the subject?  Certainly not.  The case for God is a cumulative one that reaches well beyond science..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I can quibble about the use of "proof" here (science doesn't deal in proof, only evidence) I'd rather take the time to extend the notion of "science" to include things like history as well as the study of morality, which moves into the next chapters.  Really, what I am thinking is that rational discourse combined with skeptical attitudes are the components that include science and these other topics.  In the case of the universe existing, perhaps an "I don't know" is the best answer we have right now, until someone is imaginative enough to find a way to determine it.  To posit the answer "I know, and it is God" requires a level of explanation and prediction far above what any theist seems able to give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moral-argument"&gt;Moral argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In discussing human value, Brierley writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It was grim stuff, admittedly, but it was a moment which exposed the problem for atheists who affirm the subjective nature of morality but then find themselves in a bind when it comes to truly horrendous acts.  They don't just feel wrong.  They &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; wrong.  Period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He concludes the chapter with,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I have tried to persuade you of two things in this chapter.  First, that humans have a real inherent worth and dignity that transcends a purely evolutionary story of how morality came to be.  Second, if humans have such a value then it only makes sense if there is someone beyond nature who can assign them such value, the God who created them in his own image.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not generally swayed by the moral argument for a few reasons.  First, I think that much is made out the subjective/objective dichotomy that someone like Sam Harris already handles consistently.  In &lt;em&gt;The Moral Landscape&lt;/em&gt;, he is able to define morality as the concern for the suffering and well-being of conscious creatures which, even if done imperfectly, coincides well with all of the sorts of problems we associate with moral choices.  In this way, he describes an &lt;em&gt;objective&lt;/em&gt; basis for morality without resorting to outside agency.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second issue is that the supposed solution - "God did it" - fails the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euthyphro_dilemma"&gt;"Euthyphro dilemma"&lt;/a&gt; - the question whether something is good because God wills it or whether God wills it because it is good.  In the former, we get the repugnant conclusion that if God commands murder it is necessarily good (the good of a dictator).  In the latter, the good transcends God so we don't need God for the existence of the good.  The only way out of this dilemma that I have ever heard is the claim that "the standard of the Good is God’s very nature" (William Lane Craig) or something similar.  This seems to me to be word games to define your way out of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final issue with the moral argument is that it seems to me that, like the argument from personal revelation, the argument itself relies on the &lt;em&gt;intuitive&lt;/em&gt; notion that there are some things that are &lt;em&gt;objectively&lt;/em&gt; wrong: things like murder and rape are objectively wrong, to deny this seems abhorrent, and everyone has this intuition.  Since, in other contexts (e.g. flat unmoving Earth), we have already seen that our intuitions fail in many situations, is it possible that it is failing here and we just don't see it?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore this line of thinking, one should notice that in the moral argument the usual extremes are always trotted out - murder and rape - and not something a bit more ambiguous. Since this argument holds a lot of emotional weight, perhaps we can explore this in a different way, and leave ourselves at least agnostic on this issue.  We have here some models of the source of morality - and I am neither promoting or denying any of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model 1: an external agent has imprinted some specific objective standards on everyone (perhaps imperfectly, like the sense of sight is imperfect). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model 2: a naturalistic process is responsible for the &lt;em&gt;perceived&lt;/em&gt; standard through evolution. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model 3: a naturalistic process is responsible for the standard (perceived or real) based on suffering/well being. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be others, but let's stick to these for a second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, all three models explain the &lt;em&gt;perception&lt;/em&gt; that murder and rape are objectively wrong. It would seem obvious from an evolutionary perspective that for social creatures, murder and rape would &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; objectively wrong. These three models all predict that we would have some divergence on more subtle issues, although I think not to the same degree. Model 1 would further imply that even on these more subtle aspects of morality there should eventually be convergence - the moral status of same-sex couples, for example. Models 2 and 3 would imply that there would be huge cultural differences between groups on the more subtle questions. Given our observations, this would seem to be evidence against Model 1 and the moral argument for God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In either case, if you have Models 1-3, a scientist would require further predictions that would help us actually distinguish between an agent-imparted standard and one without, even when both are consistent with our intuition about the extreme moral questions.  To say more would be presuming what the data would be without actually testing it.  We land, then, at least on the side of unconvinced but perhaps hopeful for the moral argument. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="human-purpose"&gt;Human purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"You and your beliefs are the product of a long chain of inevitable physical events. [...] It's all just a series of physical events - billiard balls bouncing off one another.  They aren't the least bit interested in the truth or falsity of the thoughts they are producing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the self-defeating nature of the naturalist worldview was a penny-dropping moment for me.  It meant that seeking meaning of any sort was a self-defeating enterprise for a thoroughgoing atheist.    Just as the collisions of the balls on the billiard-table only mean anything if there is a player who intended them to find a pocket, so we must be more than the matter that makes up our brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, I think Brierley is failing from a lack of imagination.  Meaning is a structure we attribute to actions and events in our lives. It seems to follow naturally from our pattern-seeking tendencies combined with our goals to increase well-being.  I find nothing too problematic with this view, even if we don't currently understand the detailed nature of consciousness.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a downside to notice for the "meaning from God" perspective, and that is the fact that the notion of eternal life in heaven makes &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; life not have any meaning, due to its finiteness.  Even if this life is supposedly a test for admission, the fact that the current life is &lt;em&gt;finite&lt;/em&gt; compared to the &lt;em&gt;infinite&lt;/em&gt; afterlife is enough to rob it of any significant meaning.  Clearly there are arguments on each side for this, but I just wanted to point out that it isn't completely clear even on the theistic perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="historical-arguments"&gt;Historical arguments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brierley nicely summarizes the historical arguments, both in the establishment of the existence of Jesus and the arguments of the Resurrection.  My largest concern with these arguments is the amount of trust that is placed in historical methods.  When confronted with the idea that we can't know the details of historical events to the level of repeatable, physical experiments, most people don't seem to take issue.  However, the claim that someone rose from the dead is something that - in a modern context - we'd want medical records, corroborating physical evidence, and we'd still be pretty skeptical that someone was putting us on.  Placing these events two thousand years ago, written decades after the events, by largely anonymous sources should make us &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; confident in the claim, not more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;minimal facts&lt;/em&gt; approach to the historicity of the Resurrection seems to be a major selling point for Christian apologists.  Although not a historian myself, I have read enough to see that this approach seems to never be used for any other historical event - why the special case?  I have personally found that &lt;a href="https://celsus.blog/2013/06/29/knocking-out-the-pillars-of-the-minimal-facts-apologetic/"&gt;the response by Matthew Ferguson&lt;/a&gt; - who is a historian - is as complete a response that one will ever find, and haven't seen anything even remotely convincing as a reply. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-atheists-greatest-objection-suffering"&gt;The Atheist's Greatest Objection - Suffering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll start my response here to point out that the argument from suffering is not the atheist's greatest objection.  &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TRB0TDq8tWE"&gt;Like Matt Dillahunty&lt;/a&gt;, in my opinion the greatest objection to the theistic claim of the existence of God is from &lt;em&gt;hiddenness&lt;/em&gt;.  True to Brierley's form, he grapples well with all sides of the issue of suffering, bringing in all of the typical theistic counter arguments - but they are all indirect.  He implores us to appreciate how the preponderance of the other arguments for God "tips the scale towards belief in God."  He puts forward the idea that the objection is baseless because of the lack of objective morality under the atheist worldview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"it's  difficult to see how the reality of a world of moral right and wrong can exist in the absence of God. But the question being asked by the atheist is a fundamentally moral one."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He appeals to mystery,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"it is a mystery we believe will be answered in a day of final justice and joy when Jesus Christ sets the world to right."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and free will, hidden purpose of suffering, and an allegory.  Books have been written on this problem, and this chapter summarizes the topic nicely.  I am not moved by it because it feels to me - like all treatments of this topic - one excuse after another with nothing to pin it down.  As Sam Harris says, one can always answer the question "is suffering and evil consistent with God?" with a "yes" - the better question to ask is, "does the suffering we observe in the world &lt;em&gt;suggest&lt;/em&gt; there is an all-knowing, benevolent God?"  To that, the answer is clearly "no".  Sure!  You can always come up with reasons for the former, but the later is much clearer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hiddenness"&gt;Hiddenness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The really big objection, in my view, is hiddenness - the lack of obvious indicators of a divine presence.  If God actually wants a &lt;em&gt;relationship&lt;/em&gt; with people then God's lack of obvious existence is completely inconsistent with that, in a way that appealing to free will, the purpose of relationship, allegory and mystery just don't work.  If you look at nearly every one of my responses, it really comes down to not being convinced due to the lack of unambiguous evidence.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on with this review, but it is long enough as it is.  I applaud Brierley's efforts in summarizing 10 years of conversations on this topic.  I totally endorse his goal of improving conversation on difficult topics; and his tone in this book and the podcast should be a model for everyone.  Perhaps Brierley's book is just one more data point of confirmation bias, and perhaps my review is also.  How do we get past that?  The best way is to have the conversations, honestly and completely, and to constantly question your own perspective.  I want to thank Brierley for his fine work and hope he continues these efforts far into the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>A Cookbook Response to Jordan Peterson</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/May/22/a-cookbook-response-to-jordan-peterson/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-05-22:/posts/2018/May/22/a-cookbook-response-to-jordan-peterson/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've reproduced below Sam Harris' incredible example of interpreting texts. Harris brought this up at the end of &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/meaning-and-chaos/"&gt;a long podcast with Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, but didn't press Peterson on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've reproduced below Sam Harris' incredible example of interpreting texts. Harris brought this up at the end of &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/meaning-and-chaos/"&gt;a long podcast with Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, but didn't press Peterson on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to compare it to &lt;a href="https://memoirsofanamnesic.wordpress.com/2010/07/01/interpreting-cain-and-abel-pt-i/"&gt;a transcript of Jordan Peterson's interpretation of Cain and Abel&lt;/a&gt;, which is representative of many of the things Peterson speaks about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://memoirsofanamnesic.wordpress.com/2010/07/01/interpreting-cain-and-abel-pt-i/"&gt;https://memoirsofanamnesic.wordpress.com/2010/07/01/interpreting-cain-and-abel-pt-i/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you read Harris' Cookbook exposition, you never see Peterson the same again.  Peterson claims that he only believes those interpretations that can be tied to four difference levels of understanding simultaneously, but I think that ends up being a smokescreen and that the same linguistic gymnastics can be done even in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="from-sam-harris-the-end-of-faith"&gt;From &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/books/the-end-of-faith/"&gt;Sam Harris, &lt;em&gt;The End of Faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with such hermeneutical efforts [...] is that they are perfectly unconstrained by the contents of the texts themselves. One can interpret every text in such a way as to yield almost any mystical or occult instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A case in point: I have selected another book at random, this time from the cookbook aisle of a bookstore. The book is &lt;em&gt;A Taste of Hawaii: New Cooking from the Crossroads of the Pacific&lt;/em&gt;. Therein I have discovered an as yet uncelebrated mystical treatise. While it appears to be a recipe for wok-seared fish and shrimp cakes with ogo-tomato relish, we need only study its list of ingredients to know that we are in the presence of an unrivaled spiritual intelligence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;snapper filet, cubed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons chopped scallions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and freshly ground black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dash of cayenne pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons chopped fresh ginger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon minced garlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 shrimp, peeled, deveined, and cubed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1⁄2 cup heavy cream; 2 eggs, lightly beaten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 teaspoons rice wine; 2 cups bread crumbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons vegetable oil; 2 1⁄2 cups ogo-tomato relish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;snapper filet&lt;/em&gt;, of course, is the individual himself —you and I— awash in the sea of existence. But here we find it cubed, which is to say that our situation must be remedied in all three dimensions of body, mind, and spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Three teaspoons of chopped scallions&lt;/em&gt; further partakes of the cubic symmetry, suggesting that that which we need add to each level of our being by way of antidote comes likewise in equal proportions. The import of the passage is clear: the body, mind, and spirit need to be tended to with the same care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt and freshly ground black pepper&lt;/em&gt;: here we have the perennial invocation of opposites—the white and the black aspects of our nature. Both good and evil must be understood if we would fulfill the recipe for spiritual life. Nothing, after all, can be excluded from the human experience (this seems to be a Tantric text). What is more, salt and pepper come to us in the form of grains, which is to say that our good and bad qualities are born of the tiniest actions. Thus, we are not good or evil in general, but only by virtue of innumerable moments, which color the stream of our being by force of repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dash of cayenne pepper&lt;/em&gt;: clearly, being of such robust color and flavor, this signifies the spiritual influence of an enlightened adept. What shall we make of the ambiguity of its measurement? How large is a dash? Here we must rely upon the wisdom of the universe at large. The teacher himself will know precisely what we need by way of instruction. And it is at just this point in the text that the ingredients that bespeak the heat of spiritual endeavor are added to the list—for after a dash of cayenne pepper, we find two teaspoons of chopped fresh ginger and one teaspoon of minced garlic. These form an isosceles trinity of sorts, signifying the two sides of our spiritual nature (male and female) united with the object meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes &lt;em&gt;eight shrimp—peeled, deveined, and cubed&lt;/em&gt;. The eight shrimp, of course, represent the eight worldly concerns that every spiritual aspirant must decry: fame and shame; loss and gain; pleasure and pain; praise and blame. Each needs to be deveined, peeled, and cubed— that is, purged of its power to entrance us and incorporated on the path of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That such metaphorical acrobatics can be performed on almost any text—and that they are therefore meaningless—should be obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Life from non-life and other conundrums</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Mar/06/life-from-non-life-and-other-conundrums/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-03-06:/posts/2018/Mar/06/life-from-non-life-and-other-conundrums/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/"&gt;Unbelievable podcast&lt;/a&gt; episode &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Episodes/Unbelievable-27-Oct-2007-Top-reasons-for-belief"&gt;27 Oct 2007 - Top reasons for belief&lt;/a&gt; there is a discussion about good arguments for God.  Two questions were raised as evidence for God that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/"&gt;Unbelievable podcast&lt;/a&gt; episode &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Episodes/Unbelievable-27-Oct-2007-Top-reasons-for-belief"&gt;27 Oct 2007 - Top reasons for belief&lt;/a&gt; there is a discussion about good arguments for God.  Two questions were raised as evidence for God that I think are telling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get life from non-life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get the personal from the impersonal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to these questions points to the properties of God, as traditionally understood.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first reaction is, even if we didn’t know the answers to these questions we would still not be in a position to make a positive claim for the explanation (e.g. God) without making the further step of obtaining evidence for the positive claim.  This is a God-of-the-Gaps move.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, although neither question is understood in sufficient detail, we have made substantial progress in understanding the &lt;a href="http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/abioprob/"&gt;origin of life&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consciousness#Scientific_study"&gt;origin of consciousness&lt;/a&gt;.  Far more progress than is made by assuming an agent simply created it.  We should avoid jumping to a positive claim without the evidence for that claim, and note our tendency to do just that in the face of mystery.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category><category term="Unbelievable Project"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting the Definitions Right</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Feb/18/getting-the-definitions-right/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-18:/posts/2018/Feb/18/getting-the-definitions-right/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I posted before about  &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://www.christiantoday.com/article/3-reasons-im-not-an-atheist-and-im-still-a-christian/111411.htm"&gt;another article&lt;/a&gt;, Justin Brierley comments on some of his observations as the moderator …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I posted before about  &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://www.christiantoday.com/article/3-reasons-im-not-an-atheist-and-im-still-a-christian/111411.htm"&gt;another article&lt;/a&gt;, Justin Brierley comments on some of his observations as the moderator of atheist-theist debates.  Some of his observations, unfortunately, are wrong.   For example,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Almost every atheist I meet wears the spectacles of 'naturalism'. It's the view that there is no supernatural dimension to existence. All that really exists is physical matter in motion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds suspiciously like “philosophical naturalism”, to which I know of &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; who ascribes.  There is &lt;em&gt;“methodological naturalism”&lt;/em&gt; which simply states that we may assume, for the moment as a practical matter, that there isn’t a supernatural realm.  We’ll continue to assume that until someone can demonstrate the supernatural.  This isn’t as much wearing “spectacles of ‘naturalism’” but the only pragmatic choice an honest inquiry can support.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to look at it is to notice that science evaluates &lt;em&gt;well-defined claims&lt;/em&gt;. We know of no method which can handle non-well-defined claims and we have yet to see a &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; of supernatural that is well defined.   Is there one?  Until someone puts forward something useful, we can proceed without including it in our descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Consequently, there is no realm of right or wrong to be discovered in life, no overarching purpose to things, no ultimate meaning to reach for in the universe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is also possibly wrong, and I dealt with it in the &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.  Even if you’re not convinced of this argument, you have to admit there is - for some people - a reasonable argument for morality under naturalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When BBC broadcaster and atheist scientist Jim Al-Khalili came on my Unbelievable? show he acknowledged: 'It's a huge philosophical question: why does nature speak the language of mathematics?'. Nobel Prize winning physicist Eugene Wigner termed it 'the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics', describing it as a 'wonderful gift we neither understand nor deserve’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are we to simply say 'pass' on this question?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is a necessary fact?  Perhaps there is an explanation, but we don’t have access to it?  God, however, is no explanation.  As Robert Price notes, you’re trying to explain unknown X with unknown double-X!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our belief in the intrinsic dignity and worth of human beings is best explained by Christianity. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights tapped into a foundational view of humanity established by our Judeo-Christian heritage, one which we jettison at our peril. Our belief in the intrinsic value of humanity can't be explained by atheism. But if we are made in the image of God, as Christianity claims, then that gives every human being inestimable value.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, the Bible itself clearly delineates superior and inferior people!  It specifies, in great detail, how one should treat slavery depending on whether they are the chosen people or not.  Furthermore, Jesus - despite some of his better messages - never speaks against that and tacitly endorses it with the &lt;a href="http://biblehub.com/matthew/5-18.htm"&gt;“not one jot of the law will be abolished”&lt;/a&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All-in-all I find Justin’s claims here, despite his good intentions, to be a testament to confirmation bias - which perhaps I am suffering from as well?  How can I tell?  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>3 Reasons Why Belief In God Makes Sense</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Feb/06/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-06:/posts/2018/Feb/06/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a new book, Justin Brierley of the very good &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt; writes about &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Articles/3-Reasons-Why-Belief-In-God-Makes-Sense"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt;. These reasons aren’t particularly compelling to me …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a new book, Justin Brierley of the very good &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt; writes about &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Articles/3-Reasons-Why-Belief-In-God-Makes-Sense"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt;. These reasons aren’t particularly compelling to me.  They are the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-existence"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Existence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Justin cites the Fine Tuning Argument, which has its best take-down in the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R97IHcuyWI0"&gt;Sean-Carroll/William Lane Craig debate&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s really an argument from physics, and the physics isn’t at all clear on whether the effect is there, or whether the interpretation of the effect is even reasonable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-value"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Value&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Justin states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why exactly do we believe that human life should be valued? Why did Jaime do the right thing – the human thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it very hard to come up with an answer on an atheistic world view. Why should humans have any more claim for special regard on the biological tree of life than a louse? There’s nothing intrinsically special about us in a universe that is blindly obeying the laws of nature. Any beliefs in objective human rights, values and morality are ultimately an illusion, a side-effect of our evolutionary history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I think &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/sam_harris_science_can_show_what_s_right"&gt;Sam Harris has the best word&lt;/a&gt; for this but &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cq2C7fyVTA4"&gt;Matt Dillahunty also does quite well&lt;/a&gt; with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-purpose"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Justin states, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atheism and Christianity tell two very different stories – one is of ultimate purposelessness and the other is of ultimate hope. Hope that there is a reason for our existence, hope that our lives mean something, the hope that death is not the end. Is it a delusion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “purpose” I think is a little less defined than I’d like, but it seems that if heaven exists then there really is no purpose for this life.  I am also not convinced that purpose requires an infinite time - that if you exist for a finite time then you can have purpose.  It may also be the case that there is no purpose - but how we feel about that should have no effect on the truth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Matter, Energy, and the Spirit</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/31/matter-energy-and-the-spirit/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-31:/posts/2018/Jan/31/matter-energy-and-the-spirit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Theists seem to critique naturalism with the claim that there is more to the universe than just "matter and energy". However, even physicists have in their models certain entities which …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Theists seem to critique naturalism with the claim that there is more to the universe than just "matter and energy". However, even physicists have in their models certain entities which cannot be categorized as either matter or energy. The quantum wavefunction is one clear example. There is also a history of introducing entities into models which later turn out to be unnecessary - "Vis viva" (i.e. life force), "phlogiston" (i.e. heat fluid), and "celestial matter" (vs terrestial matter). It is not that scientists are dogmatically against such entities, it's just that they should be dropped when they don't explain and predict anything or alternative explanations are simpler and more direct. We don't use agency to explain the motion of the planets anymore, for example, but we once did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other entities in models which serve as placeholders for the unknown, for example "dark matter". No one seriously thinks labeling the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galaxy_rotation_curve"&gt;gravitational effect observed from galactic rotation curves&lt;/a&gt; is better understood once we label it "dark matter". It is just a placeholder, until we figure out what dark matter actually is - neutrinos, black holes, altered gravitation on large scale, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this backdrop, what explanative and predictive power do the terms "spirit" and "supernatural agency" have anymore? Can we name anything that we understand better with their inclusion than we do without? What direct observations make these entities useful in any model of the universe, beyond as a placeholder for the unknown?  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Naturalism Defined</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/22/naturalism-defined/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-22:/posts/2018/Jan/22/naturalism-defined/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The question of supernatural vs. natural has come up a lot in discussions with Christians. Such quotes as "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naturalism_(philosophy)"&gt;Naturalism&lt;/a&gt; is ambiguous. What is nature and what isn't nature?", "Naturalism is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The question of supernatural vs. natural has come up a lot in discussions with Christians. Such quotes as "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naturalism_(philosophy)"&gt;Naturalism&lt;/a&gt; is ambiguous. What is nature and what isn't nature?", "Naturalism is vacuous. It's only tenet is an entirely reactionary one - no theology", and "Naturalism is unable to ground its own intelligibility which means it collapses into nihilism" abound.  Philosopher  Alvin Plantinga has an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_argument_against_naturalism"&gt;Evolutionary argument against naturalism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see it is the following.  There used to be a distinction between "terrestrial" and "celestial" matter. Then it was determined that the planets obeyed the same rules as the apples falling from trees and the need for the distinction disappeared. "Celestial" matter disappeared as did "terrestrial" matter leaving just "matter". Since then, we have determined, that pretty much everything we can observe follows the same rules - although some get blurred at different scales (microscopic vs macroscopic, for example). Naturalism then is simply the recognition that the stuff we see day-to-day operates on the same principles as the stars in the early universe, and the galaxies far far away. So if you can show us something that is observable yet doesn't follow these rules - something which follows a separate set of rules - then perhaps it might be time to introduce the distinction between natural and supernatural. Otherwise, there is no need for the added concept of the supernatural. Is there such an observable? What are its rules?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side-note, this means that naturalism need not "ground its own intelligibility". It is just the recognition that we can develop rules using the material on the Earth and make predictions over a wide range of time and space. There really isn't anything more we could ask of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Where probabilities and theology meet</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/posts/2018/Jan/09/where-probabilities-and-theology-meet/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-09:/posts/2018/Jan/09/where-probabilities-and-theology-meet/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We start with the article &lt;a href="https://calumsblog.com/2012/02/18/resurrection-for-theism/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the resurrection data can be evidence for theism, and why arguments for resurrection need not presuppose theism – formal demonstrations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We start with the article &lt;a href="https://calumsblog.com/2012/02/18/resurrection-for-theism/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the resurrection data can be evidence for theism, and why arguments for resurrection need not presuppose theism –
formal demonstrations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary-of-the-article"&gt;Summary of the article&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; = theism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; = the resurrection of Jesus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt; = specific historical data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some definitions, and initial probability assessments.  The numbers are not meant to be precise but to convey overall qualitative estimates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T) \ge 0.01\)&lt;/span&gt; which includes natural theology &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\sim T) = 1- P(T) \le 0.99\)&lt;/span&gt; - prior on atheism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|T) \approx 0.0001\)&lt;/span&gt; - unlikely but not extraordinarily so&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|\sim T) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt; - very unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|R) \approx 0.75\)&lt;/span&gt; - relatively high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|\sim R) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt; - very unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now some calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability of the data on atheism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(D|\sim T) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; P(D| \sim T \cdot R)P(R|\sim T)+P(D| \sim T \cdot \sim R)P(\sim R|\sim T) \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 0.75 \cdot 0.00000001 + 0.00000001 \cdot 0.999999999 \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.00000007501
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability of the data on theism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(D|T) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; P(D| T \cdot R)P(R|T)+P(D|T \cdot \sim R)P(\sim R|T) \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 0.75 \cdot 0.0001 + 0.00000001 \cdot 0.9999 \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.00007501
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From which follows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(T|D) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{P(D|T)P(T)}{P(D|T)P(T)+P(D|\sim T)P(\sim T)} \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;\frac{0.0000751 \cdot 0.01}{0.0000751 \cdot 0.01 + 0.0000000751 \cdot 0.99} \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.977
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where the prior probability for theism was &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)=0.01\)&lt;/span&gt; - definitely an increase in probability given the data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of this argument is to "&lt;em&gt;serve as a rejoinder to those philosophers of religion who do not see the argument from miracles as supporting theism at all, or who think that one need to presuppose theism to argue for a miracle&lt;/em&gt;".  Further, "&lt;em&gt;I am not intending to argue that the probabilities given at the start are correct, only that it is in principle very much possible for one to argue to theism from miracle evidence&lt;/em&gt;" and "&lt;em&gt;that it is also possible to argue for a particular miracle without presupposing theism.&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="two-concerns-with-this-argument"&gt;Two concerns with this argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lack-of-well-defined-propositions"&gt;Lack of well-defined propositions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probability theory only applies to well-defined propositions.  Something like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)\)&lt;/span&gt; may not mean anything if the proposition &lt;em&gt;theism is true&lt;/em&gt;, shortened to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; is not well defined.  If we are opening it up to all possible theisms, then we have to include deism, good gods, evil gods (think Cthulhu), chaotic gods (think Zeus), multiple gods (think Hinduism), gods as nature (think paganism), etc...  It is unclear to me that, if you include all of that, that you can easily estimate &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, quantities such as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|T)\)&lt;/span&gt; become much lower if you include all of those other pieces of theism, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt;.  I may in the future go through the calculation explicitely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lack-of-a-connection-from-data-to-propositions"&gt;Lack of a connection from data to propositions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What counts as "data" here and how does it connect to the propositions?  For example, the only "data" I know concerning the resurrection are &lt;em&gt;claims&lt;/em&gt; from people, &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; (possibly decades) after the event, from non eye-witnesses.  So when Calum writes &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|\sim R) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt;  (very unlikely), he is clearly wrong.  This sort of terrible evidence for the event is exactly what we'd expect if the event didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also part of the "data" has to be what we &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; see - official reports from Romans, mentions (either positive or negative) from contemporaries, physical evidence of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; kind, etc...  When Calum states something like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|R) \approx 0.75\)&lt;/span&gt; (very likely), he isn't taking this into account at all.  If the resurrection had actually happened, and the body was in fact missing from a guarded tomb, I would expect Paul to mention it and the trials in Acts to mention it.  Here, the missing data works &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; the claim and the proposed probabilities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="religion"></category></entry></feed>