<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - religion</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/religion.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Life from non-life and other conundrums</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/life-from-non-life-and-other-conundrums.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-03-06:/life-from-non-life-and-other-conundrums.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/"&gt;Unbelievable podcast&lt;/a&gt; episode &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Episodes/Unbelievable-27-Oct-2007-Top-reasons-for-belief"&gt;27 Oct 2007 - Top reasons for belief&lt;/a&gt; there is a discussion about good arguments for God.  Two questions were raised as evidence for God that I think are telling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get life from non-life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get the personal from the impersonal …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/"&gt;Unbelievable podcast&lt;/a&gt; episode &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Episodes/Unbelievable-27-Oct-2007-Top-reasons-for-belief"&gt;27 Oct 2007 - Top reasons for belief&lt;/a&gt; there is a discussion about good arguments for God.  Two questions were raised as evidence for God that I think are telling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get life from non-life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you get the personal from the impersonal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to these questions points to the properties of God, as traditionally understood.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first reaction is, even if we didn’t know the answers to these questions we would still not be in a position to make a positive claim for the explanation (e.g. God) without making the further step of obtaining evidence for the positive claim.  This is a God-of-the-Gaps move.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, although neither question is understood in sufficient detail, we have made substantial progress in understanding the &lt;a href="http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/abioprob/"&gt;origin of life&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consciousness#Scientific_study"&gt;origin of consciousness&lt;/a&gt;.  Far more progress than is made by assuming an agent simply created it.  We should avoid jumping to a positive claim without the evidence for that claim, and note our tendency to do just that in the face of mystery.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Getting the Definitions Right</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/getting-the-definitions-right.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-18:/getting-the-definitions-right.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I posted before about  &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://www.christiantoday.com/article/3-reasons-im-not-an-atheist-and-im-still-a-christian/111411.htm"&gt;another article&lt;/a&gt;, Justin Brierley comments on some of his observations as the moderator of atheist-theist debates.  Some of his observations, unfortunately, are wrong.   For example,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Almost every atheist I meet wears the spectacles …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I posted before about  &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://www.christiantoday.com/article/3-reasons-im-not-an-atheist-and-im-still-a-christian/111411.htm"&gt;another article&lt;/a&gt;, Justin Brierley comments on some of his observations as the moderator of atheist-theist debates.  Some of his observations, unfortunately, are wrong.   For example,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Almost every atheist I meet wears the spectacles of 'naturalism'. It's the view that there is no supernatural dimension to existence. All that really exists is physical matter in motion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds suspiciously like “philosophical naturalism”, to which I know of &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; who ascribes.  There is &lt;em&gt;“methodological naturalism”&lt;/em&gt; which simply states that we may assume, for the moment as a practical matter, that there isn’t a supernatural realm.  We’ll continue to assume that until someone can demonstrate the supernatural.  This isn’t as much wearing “spectacles of ‘naturalism’” but the only pragmatic choice an honest inquiry can support.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to look at it is to notice that science evaluates &lt;em&gt;well-defined claims&lt;/em&gt;. We know of no method which can handle non-well-defined claims and we have yet to see a &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; of supernatural that is well defined.   Is there one?  Until someone puts forward something useful, we can proceed without including it in our descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Consequently, there is no realm of right or wrong to be discovered in life, no overarching purpose to things, no ultimate meaning to reach for in the universe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is also possibly wrong, and I dealt with it in the &lt;a href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.  Even if you’re not convinced of this argument, you have to admit there is - for some people - a reasonable argument for morality under naturalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When BBC broadcaster and atheist scientist Jim Al-Khalili came on my Unbelievable? show he acknowledged: 'It's a huge philosophical question: why does nature speak the language of mathematics?'. Nobel Prize winning physicist Eugene Wigner termed it 'the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics', describing it as a 'wonderful gift we neither understand nor deserve’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are we to simply say 'pass' on this question?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is a necessary fact?  Perhaps there is an explanation, but we don’t have access to it?  God, however, is no explanation.  As Robert Price notes, you’re trying to explain unknown X with unknown double-X!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our belief in the intrinsic dignity and worth of human beings is best explained by Christianity. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights tapped into a foundational view of humanity established by our Judeo-Christian heritage, one which we jettison at our peril. Our belief in the intrinsic value of humanity can't be explained by atheism. But if we are made in the image of God, as Christianity claims, then that gives every human being inestimable value.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, the Bible itself clearly delineates superior and inferior people!  It specifies, in great detail, how one should treat slavery depending on whether they are the chosen people or not.  Furthermore, Jesus - despite some of his better messages - never speaks against that and tacitly endorses it with the &lt;a href="http://biblehub.com/matthew/5-18.htm"&gt;“not one jot of the law will be abolished”&lt;/a&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All-in-all I find Justin’s claims here, despite his good intentions, to be a testament to confirmation bias - which perhaps I am suffering from as well?  How can I tell?  &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>3 Reasons Why Belief In God Makes Sense</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-06:/3-reasons-why-belief-in-god-makes-sense.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a new book, Justin Brierley of the very good &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt; writes about &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Articles/3-Reasons-Why-Belief-In-God-Makes-Sense"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt;. These reasons aren’t particularly compelling to me.  They are the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-existence"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Existence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Justin cites the Fine Tuning Argument, which has its …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a new book, Justin Brierley of the very good &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable" title="Unbelievable Podcast"&gt;Unbelievable Podcast&lt;/a&gt; writes about &lt;a href="https://www.premierchristianradio.com/Shows/Saturday/Unbelievable/Articles/3-Reasons-Why-Belief-In-God-Makes-Sense"&gt;3 Reasons Why Belief in God Makes Sense&lt;/a&gt;. These reasons aren’t particularly compelling to me.  They are the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-existence"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Existence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Justin cites the Fine Tuning Argument, which has its best take-down in the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R97IHcuyWI0"&gt;Sean-Carroll/William Lane Craig debate&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s really an argument from physics, and the physics isn’t at all clear on whether the effect is there, or whether the interpretation of the effect is even reasonable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-value"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Value&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Justin states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why exactly do we believe that human life should be valued? Why did Jaime do the right thing – the human thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it very hard to come up with an answer on an atheistic world view. Why should humans have any more claim for special regard on the biological tree of life than a louse? There’s nothing intrinsically special about us in a universe that is blindly obeying the laws of nature. Any beliefs in objective human rights, values and morality are ultimately an illusion, a side-effect of our evolutionary history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I think &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/sam_harris_science_can_show_what_s_right"&gt;Sam Harris has the best word&lt;/a&gt; for this but &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cq2C7fyVTA4"&gt;Matt Dillahunty also does quite well&lt;/a&gt; with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="god-makes-sense-of-human-purpose"&gt;God Makes Sense Of Human Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Justin states, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atheism and Christianity tell two very different stories – one is of ultimate purposelessness and the other is of ultimate hope. Hope that there is a reason for our existence, hope that our lives mean something, the hope that death is not the end. Is it a delusion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “purpose” I think is a little less defined than I’d like, but it seems that if heaven exists then there really is no purpose for this life.  I am also not convinced that purpose requires an infinite time - that if you exist for a finite time then you can have purpose.  It may also be the case that there is no purpose - but how we feel about that should have no effect on the truth.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Matter, Energy, and the Spirit</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/matter-energy-and-the-spirit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-31:/matter-energy-and-the-spirit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theists seem to critique naturalism with the claim that there is more to the universe than just "matter and energy". However, even physicists have in their models certain entities which cannot be categorized as either matter or energy. The quantum wavefunction is one clear example. There is also a history …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theists seem to critique naturalism with the claim that there is more to the universe than just "matter and energy". However, even physicists have in their models certain entities which cannot be categorized as either matter or energy. The quantum wavefunction is one clear example. There is also a history of introducing entities into models which later turn out to be unnecessary - "Vis viva" (i.e. life force), "phlogiston" (i.e. heat fluid), and "celestial matter" (vs terrestial matter). It is not that scientists are dogmatically against such entities, it's just that they should be dropped when they don't explain and predict anything or alternative explanations are simpler and more direct. We don't use agency to explain the motion of the planets anymore, for example, but we once did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other entities in models which serve as placeholders for the unknown, for example "dark matter". No one seriously thinks labeling the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galaxy_rotation_curve"&gt;gravitational effect observed from galactic rotation curves&lt;/a&gt; is better understood once we label it "dark matter". It is just a placeholder, until we figure out what dark matter actually is - neutrinos, black holes, altered gravitation on large scale, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this backdrop, what explanative and predictive power do the terms "spirit" and "supernatural agency" have anymore? Can we name anything that we understand better with their inclusion than we do without? What direct observations make these entities useful in any model of the universe, beyond as a placeholder for the unknown?  &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Naturalism Defined</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/naturalism-defined.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-22:/naturalism-defined.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of supernatural vs. natural has come up a lot in discussions with Christians. Such quotes as "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naturalism_(philosophy)"&gt;Naturalism&lt;/a&gt; is ambiguous. What is nature and what isn't nature?", "Naturalism is vacuous. It's only tenet is an entirely reactionary one - no theology", and "Naturalism is unable to ground its own intelligibility …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="naturalism" src="images/Fallen_Monarchs_1886_by_William_Bliss_Baker.jpg"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of supernatural vs. natural has come up a lot in discussions with Christians. Such quotes as "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naturalism_(philosophy)"&gt;Naturalism&lt;/a&gt; is ambiguous. What is nature and what isn't nature?", "Naturalism is vacuous. It's only tenet is an entirely reactionary one - no theology", and "Naturalism is unable to ground its own intelligibility which means it collapses into nihilism" abound.  Philosopher  Alvin Plantinga has an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_argument_against_naturalism"&gt;Evolutionary argument against naturalism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see it is the following.  There used to be a distinction between "terrestrial" and "celestial" matter. Then it was determined that the planets obeyed the same rules as the apples falling from trees and the need for the distinction disappeared. "Celestial" matter disappeared as did "terrestrial" matter leaving just "matter". Since then, we have determined, that pretty much everything we can observe follows the same rules - although some get blurred at different scales (microscopic vs macroscopic, for example). Naturalism then is simply the recognition that the stuff we see day-to-day operates on the same principles as the stars in the early universe, and the galaxies far far away. So if you can show us something that is observable yet doesn't follow these rules - something which follows a separate set of rules - then perhaps it might be time to introduce the distinction between natural and supernatural. Otherwise, there is no need for the added concept of the supernatural. Is there such an observable? What are its rules?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side-note, this means that naturalism need not "ground its own intelligibility". It is just the recognition that we can develop rules using the material on the Earth and make predictions over a wide range of time and space. There really isn't anything more we could ask of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Where probabilities and theology meet</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/where-probabilities-and-theology-meet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-09:/where-probabilities-and-theology-meet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="theology" src="images/Bibliology-Bible-Theology-Magnifying-Glass-162886.jpg"&gt; We start with the article &lt;a href="https://calumsblog.com/2012/02/18/resurrection-for-theism/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the resurrection data can be evidence for theism, and why arguments for resurrection need not presuppose theism – formal demonstrations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="theology" src="images/Bibliology-Bible-Theology-Magnifying-Glass-162886.jpg"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with the article &lt;a href="https://calumsblog.com/2012/02/18/resurrection-for-theism/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the resurrection data can be evidence for theism, and why arguments for resurrection need not presuppose theism –
formal demonstrations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary-of-the-article"&gt;Summary of the article&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; = theism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; = the resurrection of Jesus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(D\)&lt;/span&gt; = specific historical data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some definitions, and initial probability assessments.  The numbers are not meant to be precise but to convey overall qualitative estimates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T) \ge 0.01\)&lt;/span&gt; which includes natural theology &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(\sim T) = 1- P(T) \le 0.99\)&lt;/span&gt; - prior on atheism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|T) \approx 0.0001\)&lt;/span&gt; - unlikely but not extraordinarily so&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|\sim T) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt; - very unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|R) \approx 0.75\)&lt;/span&gt; - relatively high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|\sim R) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt; - very unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now some calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability of the data on atheism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(D|\sim T) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; P(D| \sim T \cdot R)P(R|\sim T)+P(D| \sim T \cdot \sim R)P(\sim R|\sim T) \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 0.75 \cdot 0.00000001 + 0.00000001 \cdot 0.999999999 \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.00000007501
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability of the data on theism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(D|T) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; P(D| T \cdot R)P(R|T)+P(D|T \cdot \sim R)P(\sim R|T) \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 0.75 \cdot 0.0001 + 0.00000001 \cdot 0.9999 \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.00007501
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From which follows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{eqnarray}
P(T|D) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{P(D|T)P(T)}{P(D|T)P(T)+P(D|\sim T)P(\sim T)} \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;\frac{0.0000751 \cdot 0.01}{0.0000751 \cdot 0.01 + 0.0000000751 \cdot 0.99} \\
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;0.977
\end{eqnarray}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where the prior probability for theism was &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)=0.01\)&lt;/span&gt; - definitely an increase in probability given the data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of this argument is to "&lt;em&gt;serve as a rejoinder to those philosophers of religion who do not see the argument from miracles as supporting theism at all, or who think that one need to presuppose theism to argue for a miracle&lt;/em&gt;".  Further, "&lt;em&gt;I am not intending to argue that the probabilities given at the start are correct, only that it is in principle very much possible for one to argue to theism from miracle evidence&lt;/em&gt;" and "&lt;em&gt;that it is also possible to argue for a particular miracle without presupposing theism.&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="two-concerns-with-this-argument"&gt;Two concerns with this argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lack-of-well-defined-propositions"&gt;Lack of well-defined propositions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probability theory only applies to well-defined propositions.  Something like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)\)&lt;/span&gt; may not mean anything if the proposition &lt;em&gt;theism is true&lt;/em&gt;, shortened to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; is not well defined.  If we are opening it up to all possible theisms, then we have to include deism, good gods, evil gods (think Cthulhu), chaotic gods (think Zeus), multiple gods (think Hinduism), gods as nature (think paganism), etc...  It is unclear to me that, if you include all of that, that you can easily estimate &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(T)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, quantities such as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(R|T)\)&lt;/span&gt; become much lower if you include all of those other pieces of theism, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt;.  I may in the future go through the calculation explicitely. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lack-of-a-connection-from-data-to-propositions"&gt;Lack of a connection from data to propositions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What counts as "data" here and how does it connect to the propositions?  For example, the only "data" I know concerning the resurrection are &lt;em&gt;claims&lt;/em&gt; from people, &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; (possibly decades) after the event, from non eye-witnesses.  So when Calum writes &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|\sim R) \approx 0.00000001\)&lt;/span&gt;  (very unlikely), he is clearly wrong.  This sort of terrible evidence for the event is exactly what we'd expect if the event didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also part of the "data" has to be what we &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; see - official reports from Romans, mentions (either positive or negative) from contemporaries, physical evidence of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; kind, etc...  When Calum states something like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P(D|R) \approx 0.75\)&lt;/span&gt; (very likely), he isn't taking this into account at all.  If the resurrection had actually happened, and the body was in fact missing from a guarded tomb, I would expect Paul to mention it and the trials in Acts to mention it.  Here, the missing data works &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; the claim and the proposed probabilities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry></feed>