<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>bblais on the web - science</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bblais.github.io/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bblais.github.io/</id><updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>10 dogmas of science dismantled</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/10-dogmas-of-science-dismantled.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-06-18:/10-dogmas-of-science-dismantled.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dogmas of science" src="images/ocean-water-1149661_960_720.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In  his &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1TerTgDEgUE&amp;amp;t=583s"&gt;talk about the limitations of science&lt;/a&gt;, Rupert Sheldrake lists the "10 dogmas of modern science" (also listed here in text  &lt;a href="http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/"&gt;&lt;a href="http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/"&gt;http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).  They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is essentially mechanical. Dogs, for example, are complex mechanisms, rather than living organisms with goals of their own. Even people …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dogmas of science" src="images/ocean-water-1149661_960_720.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In  his &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1TerTgDEgUE&amp;amp;t=583s"&gt;talk about the limitations of science&lt;/a&gt;, Rupert Sheldrake lists the "10 dogmas of modern science" (also listed here in text  &lt;a href="http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/"&gt;&lt;a href="http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/"&gt;http://wariscrime.com/new/the-ten-dogmas-of-modern-science/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).  They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is essentially mechanical. Dogs, for example, are complex mechanisms, rather than living organisms with goals of their own. Even people are machines, ‘lumbering robots’, in Richard Dawkins’s vivid phrase, with brains that are like genetically programmed computers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All matter is unconscious. It has no inner life or subjectivity or point of view. Even human consciousness is an illusion produced by the material activities of brains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The total amount of matter and energy is always the same (with the exception of the Big Bang, when all the matter and energy of the universe suddenly appeared).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The laws of nature are fixed. They are the same today as they were at the beginning, and they will stay the same for ever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nature is purposeless, and evolution has no goal or direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All biological inheritance is material, carried in the genetic material, DNA, and in other material structures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minds are inside heads and are nothing but the activities of brains. When you look at a tree, the image of the tree you are seeing is not ‘out there’, where it seems to be, but inside your brain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memories are stored as material traces in brains and are wiped out at death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unexplained phenomena like telepathy are illusory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanistic medicine is the only kind that really works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are presented as dogmas, unquestioned by scientists and taken for granted.  Many of these are demonstrably false or misleading.  When he states (1) that animals and people "are complex mechanisms, rather than living organisms with goals of their own", this is an either-or fallacy.  They could be &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; mechanisms and agents.  It could be that we use different vocabulary on different scales - I don't describe baseball in terms of quantum mechanics, even though I am confident that all the components of baseball is governed by quantum mechanics.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheldrake lists a number of things which are poorly understood, for which there is a growing list of research, the conclusions of which are not taken dogmatically.  Similarly, there are a number of things in the list where research has been done, and the current perspective (not dogma!) has been arrived at because there has been no evidence to support the alternatives that Sheldrake is implying.   Examples of these include (2) "All matter is unconscious", (8) "Memories are stored as material traces", (5) "evolution has no goal", (7) "Minds are inside heads".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With (3), although energy is conserved (in a closed system) and matter is a subset of energy, it is not believed that the Big Bang &lt;em&gt;produced&lt;/em&gt; energy.  Rather, if the universe came from nothing then the total energy of the universe must be zero - which it empirically seems to be.  If the universe did not come from nothing, but came out of a universe-producing process then the energy didn’t “suddenly appear” as Sheldrake suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As to (4), the so-called fixed laws of Nature are a theory - which explains and is consistent with a huge variety of observations.  Thus, we are &lt;em&gt;confident&lt;/em&gt; in this particular theory.  It is possible, though, that the laws to change - and that would be measurable.  It is not taken as a dogma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point (9) "Unexplained phenomena like telepathy are illusory" is misleading, given its incompleteness.  It seems that, given &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; of observation, telepathy is in fact illusory.  However, there are many unexplained phenomena that are not illusory, e.g. dark matter, the placebo effect, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every one of these cases, scientists don't hold these as &lt;em&gt;dogmas&lt;/em&gt;.  If you have evidence, then present it!  If it turns out that you can demonstrate telepathy, that would be fantastic - but everyone who has tried so far has not been able to demonstrate it.  It may be that the universe has purpose, and perhaps it is possible to differentiate a process with a purpose from one without in certain circumstances, but the person making the claim of the extra “purpose” must be the one to bear the burden of proof. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is easier for Sheldrake to accuse someone of a dogmatic view rather than do the hard work of actually convincing them with evidence.  Just because I disagree with you doesn't mean that I am dogmatically holding to my view - you just haven't done your homework. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="science"></category></entry><entry><title>Physics Lab Ideas - Structure or No?</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/physics-lab-ideas-structure-or-no.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-26:/physics-lab-ideas-structure-or-no.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="critical thinking" src="images/Science-Background-Fractal-Physics-Abstract-1280081.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years I have taught introductory physics labs and I have seen that most “canned” labs offer very little to the student in the form of learning.  I summarize them as “here is something known quite well, and you are going to measure it badly”.  Labs measuring the acceleration …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="critical thinking" src="images/Science-Background-Fractal-Physics-Abstract-1280081.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years I have taught introductory physics labs and I have seen that most “canned” labs offer very little to the student in the form of learning.  I summarize them as “here is something known quite well, and you are going to measure it badly”.  Labs measuring the acceleration due to gravity, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(g\)&lt;/span&gt;, falls into that category.  How do you improve these sorts of labs?  I have a few ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;choose problems where the answer isn’t known or known well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;push the limit of a particular simple case into the area where the simple case breaks down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have the students design the lab themselves to answer a question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for the case of the acceleration due to gravity, put it as a model comparison problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model 1 = objects fall with a constant &lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model 2 = objects fall with a constant &lt;em&gt;acceleration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you give objects to the students such as pennies, packing peanuts, coffee filters, marbles, etc…  Some objects might be best explained with Model 2 while others with Model 1.  Neither model may describe some perfectly.  How can you tell?  Having the students design the resulting tests makes the laboratory experience a lot more interesting.  I’ll add a selfish note that it makes the labs more interesting &lt;em&gt;for the instructor&lt;/em&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Sea Slug Brains</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/sea-slug-brains.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-02-07:/sea-slug-brains.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="critical thinking" src="images/Sea_Squirt.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a somewhat disturbing fact about sea squirts recently - once they find their permanent home &lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/choke/201207/how-humans-learn-lessons-the-sea-squirt"&gt;they eat their own brain&lt;/a&gt; because they don’t need it anymore - their brain becomes a resource-heavy extraneous organ.  Yikes!  The article continues to explore the idea of how “Our body and mind are …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="critical thinking" src="images/Sea_Squirt.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a somewhat disturbing fact about sea squirts recently - once they find their permanent home &lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/choke/201207/how-humans-learn-lessons-the-sea-squirt"&gt;they eat their own brain&lt;/a&gt; because they don’t need it anymore - their brain becomes a resource-heavy extraneous organ.  Yikes!  The article continues to explore the idea of how “Our body and mind are tightly connected. The body is an important part of the learning process.”, a concept which is not stressed enough.  &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>I'm not a Denier, I'm a Skeptic</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/im-not-a-denier-im-a-skeptic.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-11:/im-not-a-denier-im-a-skeptic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="skeptic" src="images/ocean-water-1149661_960_720.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this tumultuous time, it is important to not demonize people who disagree with you.  It is also important to recognize that people can have nuanced views on complex subjects. Calling someone a denier when they have such views is not constructive.  For example, from &lt;a href="http://judithcurry.com/2015/04/28/making-nonsense-of-climate-denial/"&gt;"Making (non)sense of climate …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="skeptic" src="images/ocean-water-1149661_960_720.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this tumultuous time, it is important to not demonize people who disagree with you.  It is also important to recognize that people can have nuanced views on complex subjects. Calling someone a denier when they have such views is not constructive.  For example, from &lt;a href="http://judithcurry.com/2015/04/28/making-nonsense-of-climate-denial/"&gt;"Making (non)sense of climate denial"&lt;/a&gt; we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists agree that surface temperatures have increased since 1880, humans are adding carbon dioxide to the atmosphere, and carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases have a warming effect on the planet. However there is considerable disagreement about the most consequential issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether the warming since 1950 has been dominated by human causes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much the planet will warm in the 21st century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether warming is ‘dangerous’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems pretty reasonable to me, and is basically the view that I have.  I have seen a lot of overblown attribution to climate (e.g. polar bears, more frequent hurricanes, more intense tornadoes, etc...).  On the other hand, I've heard some ridiculous anti-climate change statements (e.g. it's cold outside now in New England therefore no climate change; people couldn't possible be influential enough to change the climate).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must be vigilant to explore each claim, evaluate it on its own, and come closer to the truth which may indeed be messy.  We need to be open to messy, nuanced positions.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Art, Scientific Reductionism, and the New Neuroscience</title><link href="https://bblais.github.io/art-scientific-reductionism-and-the-new-neuroscience.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Blais</name></author><id>tag:bblais.github.io,2018-01-10:/art-scientific-reductionism-and-the-new-neuroscience.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="skeptic" src="images/photo_72511_landscape_650x433.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href="http://chronicle.com/article/How-Art-Reveals-the-Limits-of/232821/?cid=cr&amp;amp;utm_source=cr&amp;amp;utm_medium=en"&gt;article in the Chronicle of Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;, Alva Noë challenges the neuroscience paradigm, summarized as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The momentous proposition is this: Every thought, feeling, experience, impression, value, argument, emotion, attitude, inclination, belief, desire, and ambition is in your brain. We may not know how the brain manages this …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="skeptic" src="images/photo_72511_landscape_650x433.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href="http://chronicle.com/article/How-Art-Reveals-the-Limits-of/232821/?cid=cr&amp;amp;utm_source=cr&amp;amp;utm_medium=en"&gt;article in the Chronicle of Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;, Alva Noë challenges the neuroscience paradigm, summarized as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The momentous proposition is this: Every thought, feeling, experience, impression, value, argument, emotion, attitude, inclination, belief, desire, and ambition is in your brain. We may not know how the brain manages this feat, but, so it is said, we are beginning to understand. And this new knowledge — of how the organization of bits of matter inside your head can be your personality, thoughts, understanding, wonderings, religious or sexual impulses — is surely among the most exciting and important in all of science, or so it is claimed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believes art doesn't follow this model,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a work of art, like the meaningful world around us, is not a mere stimulus. And we work hard — we look, we ask, we think, we collaborate — to bring art and world into focus for consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then critiques neuroscience as claiming that the picture and the object are the same,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equivalency of a picture and what it depicts, however, is deeply implausible.[...]You may see a woman in the statuette. But you are not in the same state you would be in if you were in the presence of an actual woman. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He continues exploring aesthetics, point out&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aesthetic responses are not fixed data points but are rather like positions staked out in a conversation, continuing in our day, our lives, and in the historical time of our culture. Aesthetic responses are cultivated and nourished, and they are also challenged. Encountering a work of art is more like an evening with a friend, or an afternoon at work, than it is like the transient relishing of a flavor. Aesthetic responses are also sometimes questions that the art poses to us rather than definitive answers; they are beginnings, opportunities, not data points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aesthetic responses, then, are not symptoms or reactions or stable quantities. They are actions. They are modes of participation. They are moments of conversation. There is nothing about which we can even ask: What are its neural correlates? And moreover, to look for neural correlates is already to have turned away from what deserves to be called aesthetic experience, for it is to have turned away from art and toward mere synaptic goings-on inside us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was reading this article, I was immediately struck by how limiting the author sees neuroscience.  The "equivalency of a picture and what it depicts" is pretty silly - there is obviously a distinction both in and outside of the brain.  We can tell the difference between a picture of an object and the object itself because internally there is a neural model which represents the object in all of the features we've experienced about the object.  This neural model is activated when a sufficient number of its properties are activated - which may be associations from other areas.  Seeing the 2D representation of a sculpture results in the neural model becoming active; seeing the 3D object as we walk around it also results in the neural model becoming active, perhaps even more strongly and with more associations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article also fails to include multiple modalities.  It is true that you can get visual responses from art, but even going to a museum to see paintings provides a more rich neural representation including smells, alternate visual angles, connections to stories about the piece, etc...  Even within the paradigm of neural models, nothing in the experience of art is inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of aesthetic responses as "actions" and "moments of conversation" is entirely consistent with the language of neural correlates.  It's just an admission that most of our experience is an interplay between internal models and actions driven by the brain's representation in such a complex fashion that we can't easily summarize it.  Scientifically, we can choose to isolate certain modalities - vision alone, for example - in order to understand pieces of it.  The scientists aren't assuming that's all there is, but it may be all that can be described at this time - at least in quantitative detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be a very interesting research project to see how the visual system is modified by learning in other areas.  Do people actually &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; art differently when they know the context or is the visual system doing the same thing in both cases but the increased aesthetic response comes from the interaction of multiple brain areas?  Far from eliminating the language of neuroscience, we should wholeheartedly embrace it.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>